<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mourners memorial in two sermons on the death of the truly pious Mris. Susanna Soame, late wife of Bartholomew Soame of Thurlow, Esq., who deceased Febru. 14, 1691/2 : with some account of her death / by Timothy Wright, Robert Fleming.</title>
            <author>Wright, Timothy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67173</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25216</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08794154</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08794154</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41864</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67173)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41864)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1272:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mourners memorial in two sermons on the death of the truly pious Mris. Susanna Soame, late wife of Bartholomew Soame of Thurlow, Esq., who deceased Febru. 14, 1691/2 : with some account of her death / by Timothy Wright, Robert Fleming.</title>
                  <author>Wright, Timothy.</author>
                  <author>Fleming, Robert, 1660?-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 127, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury and John Harris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within mourning border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Soame, Susanna, d. 1692.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41864:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>MO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNERS Memorial,</hi> IN TWO SERMONS; On the Death of the Truly Pious Mris. <hi>SUSANNA SOAME,</hi> Late Wife of <hi>Bartholomew Soame of Thurlow,</hi> Eſq; Who Deceaſed <hi>Febru.</hi> 14. 1691/2.</p>
            <p>With ſome Account of Her LIFE &amp; DEATH.</p>
            <p>By
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Timothy Wright,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Fleming,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Salusbury</hi> at the <hi>Riſing-Sun</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> and <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41864:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41864:2"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured <hi>BARTHOLOMEW SOAME</hi> of <hi>Little Thurlow,</hi> Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THat Relation which theſe Diſcourſes have to One who a few days ago ſtood in the</hi> neareſt <hi>upon earth to your ſelf, rendering them peculiarly</hi> Yours, <hi>doth intitle them to your Patronage; And conſidering that upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they may be acceptable to many others unto whom her Memory is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, tho' as they are</hi> Ours <hi>we have little reaſon to expect they ſhould be ſo to any: We do with the greater rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, in Obedience to your Commands, here humbly preſent them to your</hi> Hand <hi>in that plain Countrey-dreſs in which they were lately directed to your</hi> Ear <hi>among many others, to whom they were in that reſpect the more ſuitable,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41864:3"/> 
               <hi>as well as to the ſolemnity of the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Hopeing that as through the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace they found ſome Acceſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your</hi> Heart, <hi>when they firſt viſited your</hi> Ear, <hi>ſo they may be of ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe by the bleſſing of God to renew, or rather fix and ſettle the impreſſions which were then made, being now again preſented to your</hi> Eye.</p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>As there is none more deeply ſenſible of the greatneſs of the loſs, which You and Yours have ſuſtained by the Death of ſo near and dear, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way uſeful a Relative; ſo there is none more ſincerely deſirous than We are, to the utmoſt of our power, to be aſſiſtant both to You and them in bearing your preſent</hi> Burdens, <hi>as far as Christianity doth oblige, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitate us to be mutually helpful</hi> to one another <hi>in</hi> fulfilling <hi>that part of</hi> the Law of Chriſt. <hi>And ſurely it cannot chooſe but be a very relieving thought to you to conſider what a vaſt diſproportion there is between your Temporal loſs, and her Eternal gain,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41864:3"/> 
               <hi>by her happy Exchange of a frail, Tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering</hi> Earthly Tabernacle <hi>for</hi> an Houſe not made with hands Eternal in the Heavens. <hi>It may very well be a comfortable Alleviation to your Grief and Sorrow under the preſent afflictive diſpenſation, when you firſt look backward and reflect upon the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weariſome and painful Exerciſes, which One whom you ſo Dearly loved, and then ſo heartily pityed, did for ſo long a time undergo in a</hi> diſtempered body; <hi>and then look forward, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that She is now Eternally freed from all, being happily arrived at that</hi> Everlaſting Reſt, <hi>where there is not only</hi> perfect eaſe, <hi>but</hi> fulneſs of joy <hi>to make it the more compleat, compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cential and delightful. That</hi> Eternal weight of Glory <hi>which ſhe is now in the poſſeſſion of doth infinitely prepon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate both her former ſufferings</hi> in a mortal body, <hi>and your preſent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy affliction and ſorrow upon her</hi> going out of it. <hi>And therefore You have greater reaſon to</hi> rejoyce <hi>than to</hi> weep
<pb facs="tcp:41864:4"/> 
               <hi>for her, in as much as ſhe is now gone unto her</hi> Heavenly Father. <hi>And tho' it cannot be denyed, but we have all reaſon to</hi> weep for our ſelves; <hi>as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ſtate of this wretched World in general, (as well as of particular Families) is ſadly to be lamented, when Perſons of Eminent endowments, and ſingular uſefulneſs in their reſpective ſtations are in ſo great numbers (as they have been of late) tranſlated out of it, as being no longer worthy of ſuch excellent Inhabitants, and ſo few in many places ſpringing up in their room: Yet even in this reſpect we have no reaſon to</hi> ſorrow as thoſe that have no hope; <hi>For, As there are in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily many pleaſant and hopeful young Plants, upon which the</hi> Bleſſing of <note place="margin">Gen. 17. v. 7.</note> Abraham <hi>is continually deſcending to make them yet more and more</hi> fruitful in every good work, <hi>that it may ſtill retain the beautiful Complexion of a</hi> Watered Garden, <hi>and</hi> all that ſee <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. v. 11. cap. 61. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> them may acknowledge that they are the Seed which the Lord hath
<pb facs="tcp:41864:4"/> bleſſed: <hi>So with reſpect to the poor adjacent Countrey, who alſo have ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a great loſs (of which they are very ſenſible) in the Deceaſe of One who, by your kind aſſiſtance and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Concurrence, was more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtrumental in procuring for them ſuch plain wholeſome food for their Souls, as they had a grateful reliſh of notwithſtanding what in that kind they do otherwiſe enjoy; We are greatly encouraged to hope that the</hi> Father of Spirits, <hi>will in his wiſe, and good Providence make up this loſs alſo to them by continuing your Affairs here in ſuch a poſture, that you may yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purſue your own</hi> beneficent and charitable inclination <hi>towards your Neighbours and Country-men, in affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them the like additional helps ſtill for their ſpiritual improvement. And in ſo doing We doubt not but You will find the Bleſſings of Heaven ſtill mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied upon your Family, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of peace and ſatisfaction in your own Spirit, in perſiſting in and reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:41864:5"/> upon ſuch a charitable piece of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Souls of men. In order whereunto both You and Yours (of whoſe numerous favours to each of us we ſhall ever retain a moſt grateful ſenſe) are with no leſs ſincerity than conſtancy recommended daily to the Compaſſionate Care of the</hi> Father of Mercys, <hi>and the</hi> God of all Grace and Conſolation, by,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your greatly obliged, faithful and humble Servants in Chriſt,
<list>
                     <item>Timothy Wright,</item>
                     <item>Robert Fleming.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Thurlow-Hall</hi> 
                  <date>March, 7th. 1691/2.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41864:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Funeral Sermon.</hi> By <hi>Timothy Wright,</hi> Chaplain in the Family.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rom. 2. 7.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>To them, who by patient continuance in well doing, ſeek for Glory and Honour, and Immortality; Eternal Life.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Which words as connected with <hi>v.</hi> 6. are thus:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Who will render to every man according to his deeds: To them, who by patient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in well-doing ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality; Eternal Life.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>IT having pleaſed Almighty God, the Soveraign diſpoſer of all things, <hi>(in whoſe hands all our times are)</hi> to remove from us, and take unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, our <hi>deſervedly Honoured, Dear,</hi> and <hi>uſeful Friend;</hi> who (as you all know) was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41864:6"/> in her life-time, not without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending and chearful Concurrence of Her <hi>ſurviving Head,</hi> very inſtrumental for the propagating the True know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt Jeſus among you, by the Preaching of the Goſpel in this place.</p>
            <p>It is now the commendable and pious deſire, and appointment of her neareſt <hi>ſurviving Relatives,</hi> that we ſhould this day here pay our laſt <hi>ſolemn,</hi> and <hi>publick Reſpects</hi> together unto her <hi>Memory,</hi> in a Sermon or two dedicated unto it. And my <hi>Station</hi> in the Family laying me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a peculiar Obligation to bear my part in this ſolemn ſervice, (tho' other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe unworthy of it;) it was not long after, I began more cloſely to apply my thoughts to the making ſome ſlender pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for it, that this Text preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſelf to my mind, as a proper ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for our moſt ſerious meditation on this ſorrowful occaſion: <hi>To them, who by patient continuance in well-doing,</hi> &amp;c. A Scripture that was eminently Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in her <hi>Life,</hi> and is now more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompliſhed, and made good to her, in her <hi>death;</hi> and upon both accounts, I hope, ſo much the more adapted for our preſent inſtruction, in Conjunction with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41864:6"/> 
               <hi>that awakening and teaching Providence,</hi> which gave the occaſion to this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> upon it: Which is deſigned both for an <hi>inſtructive leſſon</hi> to the <hi>living,</hi> and a <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Memorial</hi> of the <hi>dead;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall endeavour, by the Divine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, to caſt it into ſuch a <hi>Method,</hi> and <hi>form,</hi> as may be in ſome meaſure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate to both parts of that <hi>deſign;</hi> but to the <hi>latter</hi> in ſubſerviency to the <hi>former,</hi> as that which is principally to be regarded in ſuch <hi>ſacred diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Words we have two things more generally offered to our ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. 1. The deſcriptive Character of the Heirs of future bleſſedneſs; they are ſuch <hi>who by patient continuance in well doing ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</hi> 2. The final Happineſs unto which they ſhall at laſt be advanced by the gracious deſignation, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their <hi>Heavenly Father:</hi> And this is briefly ſum'd up in thoſe two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive words, <hi>Eternal life;</hi> which indeed are both too big for our thoughts in this dark, imperfect ſtate, and are only throughly underſtood, where what is ſignified by them is fully enjoyed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Character</hi> of the Perſons here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41864:7"/> of is full, &amp; extenſive, the <hi>felicity</hi> that awaits them at the end of their courſe is great and glorious, and the <hi>Connection</hi> that is between them is firm and certain, reſulting from that divine <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is ſpoken of in the preceding part of the Context, that <hi>righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God,</hi> whereby he makes a true Eſtimate of Perſons and actions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proper Rules of Judgment; and will therefore <hi>render to every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deeds.</hi> And ſo with little variation, we may ſumme up the ſenſe of the Words in this <hi>Doctrinal Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That all they, who by patient continuance in well-doing ſeek for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality, ſhall at laſt obtain the full poſſeſſion of what they ſeek after in Eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a Concluſion of that indubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble certainty, that the Truth of it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be call'd in queſtion without deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at once the divine <hi>veracity,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munerative juſtice;</hi> for as much as the written word of God, (according to which his final diſtribution of <hi>Eternal Rewards</hi> and puniſhments, ſhall be made at the laſt day) hath expreſly declared that it ſhall be thus: And that in many
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41864:7"/> other places of Scripture as well as in the Text: And therefore looking upon it as altogether needleſs to inſiſt upon the <hi>direct proof,</hi> or Confirmation of this Truth, amongſt thoſe that do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>divine Authority</hi> of the Holy Scriptures, and believe them to be <hi>the Word of God:</hi> All that I ſhall do further in ſpeaking to it, ſhall be, firſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and then to apply it to our ſelves on this ſorrowful occaſion.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Explication</hi> there are three things to be diſtinctly conſidered and ſpoken to, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Extenſive import of the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,</hi> by which the Heirs of future bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs are here deſcribed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The nature and Excellency of that <hi>final happineſs,</hi> which doth by the divine Ordination and appointment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them as their <hi>everlaſting inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. What kind of <hi>connection</hi> there is between the one, and the other, <hi>i. e.</hi> between the <hi>qualifications</hi> imported in this <hi>Character,</hi> and that <hi>felicity,</hi> to which all that bear it ſhall at laſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41864:8"/>
            <p>1. That which doth moſt fitly come under our conſideration in the firſt place, is the extenſive import of their <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Character,</hi> who are here ſpoken of. And as in the general, we ſee they are deſcribed by the Spiritual, and Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tendency and ſcope of their deſires and aims; which are too <hi>high</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to this <hi>lower World,</hi> or to take up their <hi>Reſt</hi> in any thing, that is meaſured by <hi>Time:</hi> So more particularly, there are three things in this <hi>Character</hi> to be diſtinctly explained. 1. The great and Noble <hi>Object</hi> of their earneſt <hi>deſire,</hi> and conſtant <hi>aim,</hi> expreſſed here by <hi>Glory, Honour,</hi> and <hi>Immortality.</hi> 2. Their Souls <hi>Actual Motion</hi> towards this <hi>Object,</hi> here expreſs'd by their <hi>ſeeking</hi> after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 3. The regular <hi>Way</hi> and right <hi>Line,</hi> in which their deſires move, and their aims are directed towards this bleſſed <hi>Mark;</hi> and that is a <hi>patient continuance in well-doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We may underſtand ſomewhat of the Excellency of the <hi>Character</hi> here given us, of the <hi>Heirs of future Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> by conſidering the <hi>Object</hi> of their earneſt <hi>Deſire,</hi> and ſteady <hi>Aim;</hi> which indeed is <hi>great</hi> and <hi>noble,</hi> well-beſeeming
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41864:8"/> the dignity of an heaven-born Soul, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Immortality</hi> (or as it is in the Greek, <hi>incorruption)</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] three words that carry a great deal in them; the two firſt expreſſing the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of what they ſeek after, <hi>Glory and Honour;</hi> and the third ſubjoyned, partly to ſet forth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity, and everlaſting duration of both, and partly to denote their own endleſs <hi>exiſtence,</hi> and continuance in the full poſſeſſion and enjoyment of them, when once they ſhall have reached the <hi>Mark</hi> at which they aim.</p>
            <p>I Shall neither trouble my ſelf, nor you with a needleſs enquiry into the more nice and critical <hi>diſtinctions,</hi> that ſome may conceive to be between theſe two words, as to the <hi>proper import</hi> of them, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour:</hi> Thus much being ſufficiently <hi>evident;</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the third word, that is ſubjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, but alſo from the manifeſt <hi>ſcope</hi> of the <hi>Text;</hi> that they are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally deſigned both together to denote that <hi>everlaſting happineſs</hi> in another World, which is in the cloſe of the verſe ſumm'd up in thoſe other two words, <hi>Eternal life;</hi> intimating that to be the <hi>great thing,</hi> which all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41864:9"/> ſervants of God and Diſciples of Chriſt do, in ſubordination to the <hi>Glory</hi> of their great Lord and Maſter, <hi>chiefly</hi> ſeek after. Yet ſo as not to exclude, from being a part of the Object of their Deſire and Aim, whatſoever in <hi>this life</hi> is neceſſary as <hi>preparative</hi> and <hi>introductory</hi> to the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> of <hi>another:</hi> Much leſs excluding whatſoever elſe there may be in that <hi>future bleſſedneſs</hi> it ſelf, which cannot ſo aptly be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of under the notions of <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> eſpecially if more ſtrictly, and properly underſtood; ſuch as that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> that inexpreſſible <hi>Joy,</hi> and that inconceivable <hi>delight,</hi> which will undoubtedly accompany the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> of that <hi>immortal</hi> ſtate.</p>
            <p>Nothing ſhort of that <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 4.</note> 
               <hi>that fadeth not away,</hi> can indeed <hi>ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately</hi> terminate the Deſires, or <hi>fully</hi> anſwer the Aims of the Perſons of that ſingular and noble <hi>Character,</hi> which we are now conſidering. It is not any <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour</hi> or greatneſs, (tho' they ſhould be advanced never ſo high in thoſe <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar dignities,</hi> which many are ſo ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to climb up unto) that can content them that ſeek <hi>the honour, which cometh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 5. v. 44.</note> 
               <hi>from God only;</hi> even that which he who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41864:9"/> is the <hi>fountain</hi> of <hi>honour and glory,</hi> doth finally conſer upon all his <hi>children</hi> when they are grown up to <hi>full age,</hi> and are put into the poſſeſſion of <hi>that inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that is incorruptible and undefiled,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">*<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Pet. 1. v. 4.</note> 
               <hi>that fadeth not away, reſerved in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for them.</hi> And therefore theſe are here expreſly mentioned in the <hi>Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> the Apoſtle gives us of them, as being what they do chiefly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other things ſeek after. But tho' theſe be the <hi>ſupreme</hi> and <hi>ultimate</hi> objects of their Heavenly deſires and aims, there are alſo other things to be conſidered as <hi>intermediate</hi> objects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; which they muſt be ſuppoſed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to ſeek after in a due ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the former. And indeed they are, in great part, but <hi>lower degrees</hi> of the ſame things. For as there muſt be ſome fainter Rays of an <hi>Heavenly divine Glory</hi> impreſs'd upon thoſe Souls in this life by the ſanctifying operations of the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> of God, which are to be more intirely glorified in that which is to come: So in proportion to the degree, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they partake of this <hi>glory,</hi> there is an <hi>heavenly-honour</hi> put upon all thoſe here, who ſhall be advanced to <hi>eternal honour</hi> hereafte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r. Whereſoever the <hi>Divine</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41864:10"/> 
               <hi>Image,</hi> which was defaced by ſin, comes to be reſtored by <hi>Grace,</hi> there is an <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory</hi> put upon that Soul; which is therefore in Scripture called a <hi>Divine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. v. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Nature:</hi> And they that partake of it are ſaid to be <hi>born of God,</hi> and <hi>born from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 1. v. 13. cap. 3. 3. 1 Joh. 5. v. 1.</note> And as there is a <hi>real internal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſtamp'd upon the Soul, when the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Image</hi> comes to be re-impreſs'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; ſo ſurely it is to be reckoned a great <hi>honour</hi> to a Man to be related to God as his <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> to be his <hi>Son</hi> not only <hi>faederally</hi> by the grace of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption,</hi> but <hi>really</hi> by <hi>Regeneration.</hi> And theſe lower degrees of <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> lead to higher, and ſo on to the higheſt of all, and conſequently are to be <hi>ſought after</hi> in ſubordination thereunto. And whoſoever is regardleſs of the <hi>former,</hi> tho' his preſumptuous pretences be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo high, cannot regularly ſeek the <hi>latter.</hi> And therefore we are by no means to ſeparate the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in conſidering the great <hi>Object</hi> of the ſincere Chriſtian's earneſt <hi>deſire</hi> and conſtant <hi>aim.</hi> Which was the firſt thing to be conſidered in this <hi>deſcriptive Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of the <hi>Heirs</hi> of <hi>future bleſſedneſs.</hi> And ſo</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41864:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That which comes in the next place to be ſpoken to is, their Souls <hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Motion</hi> towards this great, and noble <hi>Object</hi> of their <hi>Deſire</hi> and <hi>Aim,</hi> as it is here expreſs'd by their <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſtudio quaerere.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeking after it.</hi> And here it will be neceſſary to ſhew more particularly what this <hi>ſeeking</hi> doth import as it hath reſpect to this <hi>Glory, and Honour, and Immortality,</hi> as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of it. And this will lead us one ſtep further towards the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the excellent, and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive <hi>Character</hi> of the happy perſons that are here ſpoken of. And it is eaſy for us to apprehend that there are ſome things neceſſarily <hi>ſuppoſed,</hi> and other things more directly <hi>imply'd</hi> in this <hi>ſeeking for glory and honour and incorruption,</hi> which ought to be conſidered diſtinctly; and therefore I ſhall give you a brief account of both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> There are ſome things to be conſidered, which it doth neceſſarily <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> and they are ſuch as theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It doth ſuppoſe a competent meaſure of knowledge, and underſtanding of what is revealed in the Goſpel concerning theſe <hi>great things,</hi> and the <hi>way</hi> in which they are to be <hi>ſought after:</hi> Together with ſome hope that they may in <hi>that</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41864:11"/> 
               <hi>way</hi> be attained. For as there can be no Rational deſire after that which we have <note place="margin">Ignoti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nulla cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido.</note> no <hi>knowledge</hi> of; So a Man will ſeek but very faintly, if at all, after that which he hath little or no <hi>hope</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth further ſuppoſe a Mind and Heart ſo far abſtracted and drawn off from the <hi>World,</hi> and its <hi>periſhing va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,</hi> as to be at the greater liberty, and leiſure to purſue theſe <hi>better,</hi> and more <hi>deſerving Objects.</hi> For it is not to be thought that a Soul that is ſo far carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, and ſunk down into the <hi>Earth</hi> as to be either drowned, and diſſolved in <hi>ſenſual pleaſures,</hi> or ſwallowed up and buryed alive in <hi>worldly cares,</hi> will with any ſerious earneſtneſs <hi>ſeek after ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>heavenly</hi> things. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſpeaks of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>ſeeking thoſe things, which are above,</hi> as a thing ſubſequent unto, as well as evidential of his being ſpiritually <hi>riſen with Chriſt.</hi> And therefore. <note place="margin">Col. 3. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It doth alſo ſuppoſe the <hi>divine ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacious grace</hi> to have been at work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Soul, in ſome meaſure enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Mind,</hi> renewing the <hi>Will,</hi> and ſpiritualizing the <hi>Affections;</hi> whereby the main bent of the Soul comes to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41864:11"/> turned towards God, whereas its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved inclination did before carry it quite another way. For as it is not to be imagined that the Soul ſhould with any ſeriouſneſs <hi>ſeek for glory, and honour, and immortality,</hi> before ſuch a <hi>Change</hi> is wrought in it: So it is certain that it could never work it in it ſelf without the powerful ſupervening operation and aſſiſtance of the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> of God. And as theſe things are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; So</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There are other things more directly implyed in this <hi>ſeeking for glory, and honour, and immortality.</hi> As</p>
            <p n="1">1. It doth imply a deliberate Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paſſed in the underſtanding upon ſufficient conviction concerning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferableneſs of theſe <hi>great things</hi> to all this <hi>World's Enjoyments,</hi> and an atual preferring and chooſing the <hi>one</hi> before the <hi>other</hi> accordingly. For all that are engaged in a ſerious, and diligent proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of thoſe things that conduce or pertain to their <hi>eternal happineſs</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> in another World, have been taught, by the <hi>Wiſdom that is from above,</hi> truly to reckon with themſelves that, all thoſe other things, upon which the minds of moſt men are ſo buſily intent,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41864:12"/> are but mean and <hi>contemptible Trifles</hi> compared with theſe: The <hi>loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lord</hi> is to them <hi>better than life it ſelf,</hi> and therefore this is <hi>ſought after,</hi> and prized by them above any of the <hi>comforts of life.</hi> To live in <hi>peace</hi> and ſweet <hi>communion</hi> with God in Chriſt here, with the <hi>lively hope</hi> of <hi>being ever with the Lord</hi> hereafter, is to them far more eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, than to have the greateſt affluence and abundance of this Worlds en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments. And therefore while others in the anxiety of their hearts are crying out, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi> They pray with the devout Pſalmiſt, <hi>Lord lift</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. v. 6.</note> 
               <hi>thou up the light of thy countenance upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth further imply an habitual <hi>heavenly-mindedneſs,</hi> whereby the main ſtream of the <hi>thoughts</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> is carryed in a ſteady current for the moſt part, towards <hi>thoſe things that are above;</hi> which therefore are the Subject of their daily <hi>meditation:</hi> As there is nothing more natural to us than to be thinking much and often upon that which is the great Object of our deſire and aim. And ſo they have <hi>their converſation in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. v. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Heaven,</hi> even while their commoration and ſtay is yet upon earth.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41864:12"/>3. It doth further imply a ſtrong <hi>emotion</hi> of ardent <hi>deſires,</hi> and earneſt <hi>longings</hi> of Soul after thoſe great and <hi>glorious</hi> enjoyments, which conſtitute the happineſs of the <hi>future ſtate;</hi> and after whatſoever is antecedently neceſſary in order to their attainment of a gracious <hi>Title</hi> unto, and <hi>meetneſs</hi> for them. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> is that <hi>Affection</hi> of the Soul where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it <hi>moves</hi> towards that, which is the <hi>Object</hi> of its <hi>Choice</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi> as it <hi>reſts</hi> in <hi>Delight,</hi> when it hath attained to the full poſſeſſion of it. And therefore the <hi>heavenly minded</hi> Chriſtian in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect ſtate, <hi>not having yet attained,</hi> is <note place="margin">Phil. 3. v. 13, 14.</note> earneſtly <hi>reaching forth,</hi> and <hi>preſſing</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>toward the Mark</hi> that is before him. And ſo there is nothing in which thoſe Noble Souls, that are ſeriouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in <hi>ſeeking for Glory, and Honour, and Immortality,</hi> do more frequently or intenſely exerciſe themſelves than in conſtant humble <hi>Addreſſes unto God</hi> by <hi>fervent Prayer</hi> for his Grace in Chriſt Jeſus to <hi>fit them for,</hi> and conduct them through <hi>preſent duty and ſervice,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal <hi>Glory and Happineſs.</hi> And then.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It doth in the laſt place imply a ſerious diligence, and Conſcientious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41864:13"/> care in the uſe of all <hi>divinely-preſcribed</hi> and appointed <hi>means</hi> for the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Spirits in all the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent habits of <hi>Grace and Holineſs</hi> here, in order to their being meetly prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and qualified in due time for the eternal enjoyment of <hi>Glory and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> hereafter; together with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dependance upon the divine Grace, implored by earneſt Prayer, for the making all ſuch <hi>means</hi> effectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to their <hi>proper end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That which we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in the next place, reſpecting the <hi>excellent Character</hi> of theſe happy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is the regular <hi>Way</hi> or right <hi>Line,</hi> in which their <hi>Deſires</hi> move, and their <hi>Aims</hi> are directed towards this bleſſed Mark: and that is <hi>a patient continuance in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] which the Vulgar Latine renders thus: <hi>[ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum patientiam boni operis,] according to the patience of a good work;</hi> or (to bring it nearer to the words of our Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) <hi>by patience in well-doing. Arias Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> renders it <hi>[ſecundum permanentiam] by perſeverance in well-doing:</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> Tranſlates it <hi>[ſecundum patientem expect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem] by patient expectation.</hi> But I think <hi>our own Tranſlation</hi> is the moſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41864:13"/> full and emphatical of them all, putting that together which is ſeverally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in them: Reading it thus; <hi>by patient continuance in well-doing;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall adhere to that; and ſo much the rather, becauſe I find the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth in Scripture ſtile ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie both <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>perſeverance.</hi> And I think the Emphaſis of it here cannot be better expreſſed than by putting them both together, and ſo underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to ſignifie <hi>patient continuance,</hi> or <hi>perſeverance with patience in well-doing.</hi> Nor do I ſee any thing in the more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate <hi>context,</hi> or in the <hi>ſcope</hi> of the <hi>Text</hi> it ſelf, to incline me to prefer any <hi>other Tranſlation</hi> of theſe words, that I have ſeen before this which we have in our Engliſh Bibles. And therefore I ſhall follow in giving you a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>way</hi> wherein the Heirs of <hi>future bleſſedneſs</hi> do <hi>ſeek for glory, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and immortality,</hi> as it is here deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, namely <hi>by patient continuance in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</hi> In which deſcription of it, we may eaſily perceive theſe three <hi>gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in it: <hi>by well-doing; by continuance or perſeverance in well-doing;</hi> and <hi>by patient continuance in well-doing:</hi> All which I ſhall ſpeak diſtinctly to in a few words, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41864:14"/> with the <hi>loweſt degree</hi> firſt. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. All that do regularly <hi>ſeek for glory, and honour, and immortality,</hi> ſeek them in the way of <hi>well-doing;</hi> which expreſſion, being <hi>indefinite,</hi> is to be underſtood in a very large extent, reaching to all the Duties incumbent upon a Chriſtian in this preſent ſtate. For as this [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or] <hi>well-doing</hi> doth in the very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal notion of it carry a reference to ſome <hi>Rule,</hi> by which what is done is to be <hi>meaſured,</hi> and to which, ſo far as it is well done, it doth accord: So it muſt be underſtood here to have a <hi>ſpecial reference</hi> unto <hi>the Goſpel,</hi> or <hi>the Law of Faith</hi> as the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>meaſure</hi> of it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>well-doing</hi> doth plainly import a ſteady <hi>conformity</hi> in a Man's Actions, as to the <hi>main bent</hi> and <hi>courſe</hi> of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, unto the <hi>holy precepts</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus lay'd down in the Goſpel, as the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>ſtandard</hi> of a Chriſtians deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſo that which is manifeſtly intended in this general expreſſion, is no leſs than an <hi>heedful attendance</hi> to all the <hi>duties of Chriſtianity;</hi> or a ſerious care &amp; ſtudious endeavour throughout the whole courſe of a Mans life to yield <hi>obedience</hi> to the <hi>Laws of Chriſt,</hi> and ſo to <hi>walk worthy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 10</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41864:14"/> 
               <hi>of the Lord unto all pleaſing.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo underſtood, it is ſo far from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding that <hi>Faith in Chriſt,</hi> whereby a ſinner doth <hi>embrace</hi> and <hi>receive</hi> him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Offer of the Goſpel, as the way to obtain Salvation by him, that it doth neceſſarily include it: Foraſmuch as this <hi>believing</hi> is an eſſential part of that <hi>well-doing,</hi> by which all ſerious Chriſtians do <hi>ſeek for glory, and honour, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</hi> And therefore our Lord himſelf doth <hi>emphatically</hi> call it [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>the work of God.</hi> It is by <hi>well-doing</hi> in <note place="margin">John 6. v. 29.</note> this comprehenſive ſenſe as it takes in both <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Good Works,</hi> in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Precepts of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that we muſt ſeek for <hi>eternal glory</hi> and <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> if ever we would obtain it. And whoſoever they be that ſeek it any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, (either ſeparating the one of theſe from the other, or careleſly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting and diſregarding both;) they will find at laſt that they did herein mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably <hi>deceive themſelves,</hi> and put a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Cheat upon their own Souls. For the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is <hi>the Author</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5. v. 9.</note> 
               <hi>of Eternal Salvation</hi> (not promiſcuouſly unto all, but only) <hi>to all thoſe that obey him:</hi> And therefore he himſelf alſo tells us, that <hi>not every one that ſaith unto him</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41864:15"/> 
               <hi>Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doeth the Will of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. v. 21.</note> 
               <hi>his Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A further <hi>gradation</hi> expreſs'd in this <hi>diſcription</hi> of the only <hi>regular way</hi> of ſeeking for <hi>future glory</hi> and <hi>bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> is that it is to be done by <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in well-doing,</hi> or by perſeverance therein unto the end. And this is no leſs neceſſary than the former: For <hi>if any man draw back</hi> it will be <hi>to his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> becauſe God hath declared <hi>he will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. v. 38.</note> 
               <hi>have no pleaſure in him.</hi> He that would <hi>ſo run as to obtain,</hi> muſt not think it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to <hi>ſet out right,</hi> to begin well; but he muſt hold on till he comes to the end of the preſcribed courſe, or elſe he looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all. As he muſt be careful to run the <hi>very race</hi> that is <hi>ſet before him,</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his feet in the <hi>direct path</hi> that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineared for him by the <hi>divine Precepts,</hi> without <hi>turning aſide</hi> to <hi>any crooked way,</hi> either on the right hand or on the left; So he muſt be ſure to run to the end of it; not deſiſting till he arrive there, or elſe he will <hi>run in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The laſt and higheſt <hi>gradation</hi> in this account that the Text gives of the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>ſeeking</hi> regularly <hi>for glory, and honour, and immortality,</hi> is made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41864:15"/> by the addition of <hi>patience</hi> unto this <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in well-doing.</hi> And this Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath reſpect both to <hi>preſent evils</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, and to <hi>future good</hi> expected in the way of our duty. For <hi>patience</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed by the Children of God in this ſtate of their <hi>minority</hi> &amp; imperfection both theſe ways, viz. <hi>in enduring</hi> and in <hi>waiting:</hi> &amp; indeed in both reſpects they <hi>have need of patience, that after they have done the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. v. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Will of God they may receive the promiſe.</hi> Firſt, All the <hi>Heirs of Glory,</hi> during the time of their <hi>minority,</hi> do ſtand in need of <hi>patience</hi> as it is to be exerciſed in <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during</hi> the many afflictive evils that they meet with in the courſe of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and <hi>continuance in well-doing.</hi> For as Gods ancient People <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſſed through a troubleſome, and howling <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> into the <hi>promiſed Land;</hi> So all. True Chriſtians muſt expect <hi>through much</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 14. v. 22.</note> 
               <hi>tribulation to enter into the Kingdom of God:</hi> And therefore our Lord Jeſus Chriſt told his diſciples, that <hi>in the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">John 16. v. 33.</note> 
               <hi>World they ſhould have tribulation.</hi> And indeed there is ſuch a great variety of troubles, to which the beſt of men are expoſed here in this life as may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently convince them, that <hi>here is not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mich. 2. v. 10.</note> 
               <hi>their reſt.</hi> But all theſe are quietly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41864:16"/> and patiently undergone with a ſilent, humble, and meek <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Soveraign <hi>diſpoſing</hi> hand that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all, by ſuch as have <hi>eternal glory</hi> in their eye and aim; in ſomuch that they do not only <hi>perſevere in doing good</hi> with unwearied diligence, but alſo <hi>hold out in ſuffering evils</hi> with invincible pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <note place="margin">Col. 1. v. 11.</note> being <hi>ſtrengthened thereunto accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the glorious power</hi> of <hi>the divine grace.</hi> Secondly, They do exerciſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in <hi>waiting</hi> as well as in <hi>enduring.</hi> For (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>they hope for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. v. 25.</note> 
               <hi>that which yet they ſee not, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do with patience wait for it.</hi> And this is that kind of patience which the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> exhorts unto. <hi>Jam. 5. 7, 8. Be patient therefore brethren, unto the coming of the Lord; behold the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it until he receive the early and the latter rain: Be ye alſo patient, stabliſh your hearts, for the coming of the Lord draws nigh.</hi> And the right Seekers after Glory and happineſs are no ſtrangers to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this kind of patience. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not <hi>weary in well-doing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know, that in due ſeaſon they ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. v. 9.</note> 
               <hi>reap if they faint not,</hi> and that every thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41864:16"/> is moſt pleaſant as well as moſt <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 3. v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>in its ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I ſhewn you at large the extenſive import of the <hi>Character</hi> by which the <hi>Heirs of future bleſſedneſs</hi> are here deſcribed. And ſo I come more briefly</p>
            <p>II. To conſider in the next place the nature and excellency of that <hi>final hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</hi> which doth, by the <hi>divine ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>appointment,</hi> belong to them as their everlaſting inheritance; as it is here ſumm'd up in thoſe two compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive words <hi>Eternal Life:</hi> Which contain more in them than all the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>eloquence</hi> of <hi>men and Angels</hi> is able to expreſs and ſet forth. It is a phraſe more frequently than any other made uſe of in Scripture <hi>ſummarily</hi> to expreſs the <hi>great felicity,</hi> to which the <hi>glorified Saints</hi> are advanced in the <hi>heavenly Manſions.</hi> And it doth very aptly ſerve to lead our Minds into ſome more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Conceptions of the <hi>greatneſs</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of it; tho' indeed all that can be ſaid or thought falls infinitely ſhort of being <hi>commenſurate</hi> unto it. Life is the ſweeteſt of all enjoyments, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that is the laſt thing that any man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41864:17"/> will part with ſo long as he is able to retain it; and <hi>Eternal life</hi> is the <hi>higheſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job. 2. ver. 4.</note> and <hi>moſt noble</hi> kind of life, of which the nature of Man when in the <hi>utmoſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> is ſuſceptive of. And the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of it will more clearly appear to us if we conſider it more diſtinctly, firſt with reſpect to what is more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly <hi>imported</hi> in it, and then with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to what it doth neceſſarily <hi>connote,</hi> when underſtood in that <hi>latitude</hi> in which the phraſe is moſt frequently (if not always) uſed in Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we conſider it in the more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect import of it, ſo it appears to have a very <hi>radiant excellency</hi> in it that doth far out-ſhine the brighteſt part of <hi>this Worlds glory.</hi> For it muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to ſingifie ſomewhat more than a <hi>bare immortality</hi> or a meer <hi>living for ever,</hi> (for that belongs alſo to <hi>the wicked that are turned into Hell,</hi> and hath no happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in it if abſtractly conſidered,) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a <hi>glorious ineffable and everlaſting uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God,</hi> the fountain of life; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, dwelling in God,</hi> the all-comprehending Spirit, do (ſo far as the <hi>finite capacity</hi> of a creature will admit) everlaſtingly poſſeſs <hi>a perfect plenitude of life.</hi> And
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41864:17"/> this is elſewhere in Scripture expreſs'd by <hi>being ever with the Lord.</hi> And this <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. v. 17.</note> we are to conceive the Souls of the Saints to enter upon immediately after death, altho' their bodies are not to be advanced to a participation in it until the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> when they alſo ſhall be made <hi>immortal,</hi> and <hi>faſhioned like unto Chriſts glorious Body, according to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. v. 21.</note> 
               <hi>working, whereby he is able even to ſubdue all things unto himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If we conſider this <hi>Eternal life</hi> with reſpect to what it doth neceſſarily <hi>connote,</hi> ſo it will appear to be ſtill more <hi>excellent</hi> and <hi>glorious.</hi> For as that God <hi>in whom</hi> the glorified Saints have moſt <hi>intimately</hi> their <hi>everlaſting</hi> reſidence, is in himſelf the <hi>fountain of life,</hi> or <hi>the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God;</hi> So he is alſo the <hi>fountain of bleſſedneſs.</hi> And therefore, as by <hi>being for ever with the Lord,</hi> they do everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly poſſeſs a perfect <hi>plenitude of life,</hi> in <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. v. 4.</note> which every thing of <hi>mortality</hi> ſhall at laſt be <hi>ſwallowed up:</hi> So they muſt needs alſo enjoy together therewith a <hi>perfect fulneſs</hi> of whatſoever can be conceived of under the notion of <hi>happineſs;</hi> a <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Glory</hi> both ſubjective and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective, glory ſhining <hi>in them,</hi> and glory ſhining <hi>upon,</hi> and <hi>round about,</hi> yea <hi>into</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41864:18"/> 
               <hi>them,</hi> transfuſing its bright beams <hi>through them; a fulneſs of honour</hi> infinitely tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending all thoſe <hi>fading Titles,</hi> which advance one man ſo high above another in this <hi>lower World;</hi> and a <hi>fulneſs of joy, ſatisfaction and delight,</hi> even thoſe pure, refined <hi>pleaſures that are at Gods right</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>hand for evermore.</hi> All this, and a great deal more that neither our <hi>words</hi> nor <hi>thoughts</hi> can reach, is <hi>ſummarily</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in that <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> which all they ſhall certainly attain at the end of their courſe, <hi>who by patient continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in well-doing do ſeek for glory, and honour, and immortality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which will more plainly appear to us by conſidering that which follows in the next place in order, namely:</p>
            <p>III. That which remains in the laſt place to be ſpoken to, is, <hi>the connection</hi> between the qualifications imported in the foregoing <hi>Character</hi> and that <hi>glorious felicity,</hi> unto which all that <hi>bear</hi> it ſhall at laſt be advanced; between a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>courſe</hi> and his <hi>crown;</hi> between his <hi>ſeeking for glory, and honour, and immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> in the way here deſcribed, and that <hi>eternal life,</hi> in which he ſhall finally <hi>enjoy</hi> all that he <hi>ſought</hi> for. That there is a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41864:18"/> 
               <hi>connection</hi> between them is ſufficiently evident, inaſmuch as <hi>the one</hi> is attainable no other way but <hi>by the other:</hi> And of what kind this connection is, I am now to ſhew. And in ſhort, It is eaſie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us to apprehend that this connection is not <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> but <hi>ordinate,</hi> not ſuch as doth <hi>neceſſarily</hi> reſult from the <hi>nature</hi> of the things themſelves that are here connected, but ſuch as hath its foundation in the <hi>gracious ordination</hi> and <hi>appointment</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> For it is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evident to any one, that doth atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and ſeriouſly conſider it, That there is no <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>adequate proportion</hi> between the moſt diligent and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chriſtians <hi>preſent ſervice,</hi> and his <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture eternal reward.</hi> And ſo it is no leſs obvious for us to conceive that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection that is between them is not foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi>Merit,</hi> but in <hi>Free Grace.</hi> For <hi>when we have done all, we muſt ſay we</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 17. v. 10.</note> 
               <hi>are unprofitable Servants, we have done only that which was our duty to do.</hi> And it is moſt abſurd for any one to think to <hi>merit</hi> any thing by the payment of a <hi>juſt Debt.</hi> And therefore the Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>eternal life</hi> under the notion of a <hi>Gift,</hi> as obtained only by the <hi>free donation</hi> of God, and not as a poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41864:19"/> accruing to us by any <hi>deſert</hi> of our own; whereas, on the other hand, that <hi>eternal death,</hi> which is the juſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sin is called <hi>Wages,</hi> as being no more than what it doth moſt iuſtly <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</hi> Rom. 6. 23. <hi>For the Wages of Sin is death: But the gift of God is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And ſo the <hi>Reward of the eternal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is ſeveral times in Scripture under the Title of <hi>Mercy:</hi> As the Apoſtle prayed for <hi>Oneſiphorus,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 18. <hi>The Lord grant unto him that he may find Mercy of the Lord at that day.</hi> And ſo we are exhorted <hi>to keep our ſelves in the love of God, looking for the Mercy of our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jude v. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt unto eternal life.</hi> And therefore it is manifeſt that the connecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is between the Chriſtians <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> and <hi>reward,</hi> his <hi>Courſe</hi> and his <hi>Crown,</hi> is not founded in <hi>merit,</hi> but in the <hi>free Grace</hi> and <hi>undeſerved Love</hi> of God in Chriſt; to which alone that <hi>gracious Promiſe</hi> or <hi>Covenant</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely owing, whereby he hath been pleaſed to eſtabliſh an <hi>immutable order</hi> between them, ſo as that the one ſhall be infallibly <hi>conſequent</hi> upon the other.</p>
            <p>But the connection is never the <hi>leſs firm</hi> or <hi>certain</hi> for being ſo founded as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41864:19"/> it is, but rather the <hi>more</hi> ſo; For the <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> which is the more immediate ground and foundation of it, is <hi>an everlaſting Covenant,</hi> a covenant not <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23 v. 5.</note> only <hi>ordered in all things,</hi> but alſo <hi>ſure:</hi> Foraſmuch as the <hi>divine eternal veraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is engaged to make good every <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> of it to as many as have regularly laid hold upon it, and by an hearty compliance with its <hi>conditions</hi> come to have a <hi>real intereſt</hi> in it. For altho' God was unlimitedly free before he made the promiſe, and eſtabliſhed his Gracious Covenant with us; yet that being once done, he is obliged, for the <hi>honour</hi> of his <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> to make it good. And ſo though in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he can owe nothing to us, he is a <hi>Debter</hi> to his own <hi>Promiſe.</hi> And at the laſt day he will be glorified not only as the free and magnificent <hi>Donor</hi> of all the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> but alſo as the <hi>God of Truth</hi> in fulfilling all the <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and precious Promiſes</hi> that he <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. v. 4.</note> hath made unto his faithful Servants. And therefore <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto them who by pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent continuance in well-doing, ſeek for glory, and honour, and immortality,</hi> he will not fail to <hi>render eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And having thus, with as much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41864:20"/> as the Subject could well admit, fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed what I propoſed to ſpeak doctrinally from this Text of Scripture; All that now remains, is to make ſome <hi>applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of what hath been ſaid, unto our ſelves. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. From hence we learn with what <hi>magnanimity</hi> and nobleneſs of Spirit true living Chriſtianity doth inſpire thoſe in whom it takes place; elevating and raiſing their minds and hearts above this periſhing World, and all its fading tranſitory enjoyments: Steadily inclin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them <hi>to ſeek thoſe things that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. v. 1.</note> inſomuch that nothing lower than <hi>heavenly glory</hi> and <hi>immortal honour</hi> can now content them, or compoſe their Deſires into a complacential Reſt and ſatisfaction. While others, that are acted by the forbid abject and baſe <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of this World,</hi> lie groveling in the duſt of this earth, drudging and toy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for what is only accommodate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their mortal part; the living Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>being made alive to God through</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt his Lord,</hi> and <hi>having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the Spirit of this World, but the Spirit that is from God,</hi> is continually <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. v. 12.</note> aſpiring upwards in heavenly thoughts, deſires and aims, ever <hi>ſeeking for glory,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41864:20"/> 
               <hi>and honour, and immortality,</hi> till he comes to the actual fruition of all in <hi>eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What hath been ſaid may ſerve alſo to diſcover to us the <hi>prepoſterous folly</hi> of their preſumptuous hopes, who think at laſt to obtain <hi>eternal</hi> life, tho' they take no care to ſeek it in that <hi>way</hi> which the Goſpel doth preſcribe, and in which only it is to be found, even <hi>by a patient continuance in well-doing.</hi> Heaven and eternal happineſs are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to none as an <hi>abſolute irreſpective Gift,</hi> but as a <hi>Reward</hi> conſequent upon <hi>ſervice;</hi> And therefore whoſoever are careleſs and unconcerned about the <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> of the preſent ſtate, will be ſure to ſall ſhort of the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>felicity</hi> of the future: And then the higher their preſumptuous and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs hopes have been raiſed, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will their ſhame and diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be when they and their hopes ſhall periſh together.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The firm and certain connection which the gracious <hi>Promiſe</hi> and <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> of God hath made and ſettled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>a patient continuance in well-doing</hi> here, and the enjoyment of <hi>eternal life</hi> hereafter, may further ſerve for the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41864:21"/> comfort and encouragement of all his ſincere and faithful Servants under all the difficulties and hardſhips, afflictions and ſorrows, exerciſes and Tryals, which they undergo here in the courſe of their obedience. He that hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a clear proſpect by faith of the inviſible World, and of the <hi>glory, honour</hi> and <hi>incorruption,</hi> which are to be <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> enjoyed there by all that regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſeek after</hi> them here; and is withal conſcious to himſelf that he is one of that happy number, can eaſily ſee through the darkeſt cloud, and diſcern a comfortable end of all his preſent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. And therefore his <hi>Faith</hi> mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly animating his <hi>Hope,</hi> and his Hope proportionably ſtrengthening his <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> he doth not <hi>faint in the day</hi> of <hi>Adverſity,</hi> nor is he weary of well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <note place="margin">Prov. 24. v. 10.</note> becauſe he is ſufficiently aſſured that <hi>the time is ſhort,</hi> and ſo that it will be but yet a little while before <hi>all Tears</hi> ſhall <hi>be wiped away from his eyes,</hi> and all <note place="margin">Iſa. 25. v. 8.</note> grief and ſorrow baniſhed from his heart, and endleſs Joyes ſucceed in their <note place="margin">Rev. 7. v. 17.</note> room.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſame conſideration may ſerve as a ſweet and comfortable allay to the ſorrows of ſuch as are mourning for the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41864:21"/> death of ſuch of their near and dear Relatives or Friends, who in their life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time gave ſufficient proof of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary care and diligence to perſevere in ſuch a ſteady courſe of duty and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience as hath eternal life and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry connected with it. It is indeed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſelfiſh and unbecoming our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hope with immoderate and unallayed grief and ſorrow to lament the death of ſuch: For aſmuch as altho' their <hi>abſence,</hi> and departure from us be very ſenſibly our great <hi>loſs,</hi> their <hi>preſence with the Lord</hi> is in an infinitely higher degree their <hi>gain.</hi> And therefore methinks even na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural affection, which makes us wiſh well to our dear Relatives, eſpecially when ſanctified by Grace and aſſiſted by faith, ſhould give ſome check to our immoderate grief for the Removal of ſuch of them from us by the ſtroke of death, concerning whom we have ſuch comfortable and well-grounded hopes. For why ſhould we grieve at or regret their happy advancement unto that <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal glory and honour</hi> which they had been long <hi>ſeeking for,</hi> but could never reach before?</p>
            <p n="5">5. What we have heard, may ſerve both for our direction and excitation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41864:22"/> ſuch a regular and ſteady courſe of obedience here, that we may all obtain <hi>eternal life</hi> hereafter. Let us endeavour therefore to have that <hi>Truth,</hi> which hath been this day ſuggeſted to us out of the Word of God, ſo deeply im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd upon our very hearts, that the thoughts of it may continually dwell with us, and have a conſtant influence upon us, by the grace of God, for the engageing us to the moſt ſtrenuous di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and conſtancy in proſecuting our <hi>preſent duty,</hi> as that which hath by the divine ordination and appointment a direct tendency to our <hi>future eternal fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity;</hi> Let us never forget that the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> and a bleſſed <hi>immortality,</hi> is a <hi>patient continuance in well doing.</hi> And ſo let none of us any longer indulge our ſelves in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of that upon which our eternal welfare doth ſo evidently depend; but <hi>let the time paſt ſuffice us to have wrought the Wills of the Fleſh,</hi> and to have miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>employed the active ſtrength and vigour of our Souls in <hi>minding</hi> only <hi>earthly things.</hi> And now let us reſolve, by the grace of God, to call off our hearts and affections from this lower World, and all its periſhing vanities, and ſo ſet
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41864:22"/> our ſelves in good earneſt to <hi>ſeek thoſe things that are above:</hi> Minding the great Duties of Chriſtianity with a more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious care than ever we have hitherto exerciſed about them: Making True <hi>practical Religion</hi> more our buſineſs, as it is what will turn to the beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt unto us at laſt: O let none of us be guilty of ſuch prepoſterous folly in the great concernments of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls, as we would be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of in the management of our ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affairs, ſeparating the <hi>Way</hi> from the <hi>End,</hi> as if the one might be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without a ſerious and due attendance to the other. The Way in which we muſt ſeek for future <hi>glory</hi> and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if ever we would have it, is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delineated to us in the Text: And all thoſe that are gone before us, and have actually received <hi>the Reward of the eternal inheritance,</hi> both ſought and obtained it in this way and no other, even <hi>by a patient continuance in well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> It doth therefore concern us to tread in their ſteps, that we alſo may in due time, and in our appointed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der come to the fruition of the ſame happineſs with them. And ſo my ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt exhortation to you is in the words
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41864:23"/> of the Apoſtle, Heb. 6. 11, 12. <hi>That every one of you do ſhew the ſame dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to the full aſſurance of hope unto the end; that ye be not ſlothful, but followers of them, who through faith and patience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the promiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here for your further excitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I ſhall now, on this ſolemn occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſet before you the illuſtrious and worthy Example of <hi>our deſervedly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and lately deceaſed Friend,</hi> whoſe immortal part is now with Chriſt. For She was indeed One upon whoſe Heart and Life the divine Spirit and Grace had in moſt conſpicuous and ſhining li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaments drawn that <hi>excellent and noble Character,</hi> by which the Heirs of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs are deſcribed in the Text; And to that in the ſeveral parts of it I ſhall principally confine my ſelf in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Account that I ſhall give you of her: Wherein my more immediate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and aim is to ſhew you how eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Text of Scripture was exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in her; that you may thence be the more confirmed in your comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and well-grounded aſſurance of her being now happily poſſeſſed of that <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life,</hi> which by the divine deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and appointment belongs to all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41864:23"/> that bear that Character. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to ſay any thing of her <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> endowments, either intellectual or moral, altho they were ſuch as made the Grace of God to ſhine with the greater luſtre in her diſcreet and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered converſation; I ſhall ſpeak on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe that were manifeſtly <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>ſupernatural.</hi> And for as much as my happy acquaintance with her did commence <hi>too late</hi> to capacitate me to give you any particular account of the more early impreſſions of the Divine Grace upon her Soul, or the more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Paſſages of her pious Life; and that I may keep my ſelf as remote as may be from all ſuſpition of <hi>flattery</hi> and <hi>falſehood</hi> in the payment of this my laſt ſolemn Reſpect unto her Memory: I ſhall only ſpeak of what I have had the peculiar advantage of obſerving my ſelf for the ſpace of almoſt ſeven years that I have (in two diſtinct periods) liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in her Family. And I muſt have been very inobſervant indeed if in all that time I had not taken notice of what was ſo viſible both in her habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Temper and conſtant carriage ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly anſwering to every part of that <hi>deſcriptive Character</hi> of the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41864:24"/> which I have been this day un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding to you; of which I ſhall give you a diſtinct and impartial account in the following Particulars. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. Her <hi>habitual heavenly-mindedneſs</hi> was ſuch a ſhining Excellency in her as could not be hid under that Vaile of <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Modeſty</hi> which was her conſtant <hi>ornament;</hi> but did diſcover it ſelf in an holy <hi>contempt</hi> of this lower World and all its periſhing Enjoyments, in a <hi>ſteady Aim</hi> directed unto higher and more noble Objects, and in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual <hi>aſpiration</hi> after <hi>glory, and honour, and immortality.</hi> The divine Grace had inſpired her with that true magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and nobleneſs of Spirit, that her <hi>Deſires</hi> and <hi>Hopes</hi> could by no means be confined within the narrow limits of <hi>Time,</hi> nor be long together held down to ſublunary and <hi>terrene</hi> objects: And therefore her Soul would be often moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upward upon the Wings of Faith into the bright Regions of light and glory above to contemplate the eternal and glorious Objects that are there; And more eſpecially toward the end of her Time, having been obſerved for ſome months before her Death to have her thoughts much exerciſed about the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41864:24"/> State and Enjoyments of Heaven: And particularly about ſeparate Souls mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al knowledge of and converſe with one another; taking occaſion very frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcourſe upon that <hi>ſublime Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> when in company with ſuch as ſhe apprehended might be aſſiſtant to her in her endeavours to attain more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and clear notions about it. Of which ſhe now underſtands more than any one here could tell her.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The earneſtneſs of her <hi>deſires</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heavenly <hi>glory</hi> and felicity was no leſs conſpicuous than the ſteadineſs of her <hi>Aims</hi> principally directed that way. She did not only ſet this <hi>glory, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and immortality</hi> before her as the great <hi>Mark</hi> at which ſhe aimed, but was continually <hi>preſſing forwards toward it,</hi> ſeeking after theſe things with the moſt cloſe and ſtrenuous <hi>application of mind.</hi> And that more eſpeically in <hi>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer,</hi> wherein ſhe was wont to breath out her very Soul to God every day: For as her natural Temper incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her to the love of <hi>Solitude,</hi> ſo Grace had taught her to make the beſt improvement of her <hi>Solitary hours,</hi> which ſhe was careful to employ not only in diligent reading and devout meditation,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41864:25"/> but eſpecially in <hi>ſecret prayer;</hi> whereby ſhe maintained and kept up a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>commerce</hi> with Heaven, which many a time brought her in very rich <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns</hi> in divine communications and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations. Nor was ſhe content to ſeek alone for ſuch great things as <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> are; and therefore would often with earneſt importunity be-ſpeak the joint-aſſiſtance of her more intimate Chriſtian-friends, and eſpecially of ſuch Miniſters of her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance as ſhe could be moſt free with, in managing this work; that ſo her Addreſſes to God might be the more ſolemn by others aſſiſting her therein, and Dedicating ſeveral hours together unto that ſacred ſervice, as hath been frequently done at her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and principally upon her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in her own houſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. She was no leſs careful about the <hi>regular way</hi> of <hi>ſeeking for glory, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and immortality,</hi> than ſhe was ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and zealous in the <hi>work</hi> it ſelf. For ſhe was better inſtructed in the great Doctrines and Duties of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and in the Method of obtaining Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Goſpel, than to ſeparate
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41864:25"/> the <hi>Way</hi> from the <hi>End,</hi> or fooliſhly to think of attaining the <hi>one</hi> without an heedful walking in the <hi>other.</hi> And therefore it was her daily Study and ſincere Endeavour in every thing <hi>to walk by rule;</hi> not abuſing the <hi>Grace</hi> of the Goſpel as an encouragement to <hi>licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> but learning from it <hi>to deny all ungodlineſs and wordly luſts, and to live</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. v. 11, 12. &amp; 13.</note> 
               <hi>ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World; ſo looking for that bleſſed hope,</hi> &amp;c. Labouring to have her <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> ſuch in all reſpects <hi>as might</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1. v. 27.</note> 
               <hi>become the Goſpel;</hi> and her behaviour anſwerable to her hope. And therefore it was her conſcientious care, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt endeavour to be ſeriouſly diligent and conſtant in performing all the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a Chriſtian, both in her <hi>perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> and <hi>relative</hi> capacities. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the latter ſhe ſometimes found ſome <hi>difficulties</hi> (under ſuch concurrent circumſtances as need not be mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) which did unavoidably diſcover ſuch of her <hi>Infirmities</hi> as otherwiſe might have been hid: I have this to add from certain knowledge, that they were by <hi>none</hi> more deeply reſented, or more ſadly bewailed than by <hi>her ſelf.</hi> For when at any time, upon ſome ſlender
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41864:26"/> provocation, the <hi>natural quickneſs</hi> of her Temper did on a ſuddain betray and hurry her into ſome more haſty, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate or indecent expreſſions, they were ſoon followed with ſuch an <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> againſt her ſelf as did more than bear proportion thereunto, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might very juſtly (as I doubt not but it did in a great meaſure) make atonement for them unto ſuch as were moſt nearly and ſenſibly touched by them. All which I ſhould have paſſed over in ſilence, had I not conſidered that what I have mentioned on the <hi>one part</hi> might perhaps have been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by many, unto whom what is ſaid on the <hi>other,</hi> in her juſt vindication, may be altogether unknown. And what I have thus impartially hinted amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſufficient evidence that her Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of this kind were no other than were very well conſiſtent with ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and a good <hi>conſcience both toward God</hi> and <hi>toward Man;</hi> I muſt after all in juſtice to her Memory give her this general Character, (which all that knew her more intimately will ſay ſhe juſtly deſerved:) <hi>That ſhe was a loving, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and prudent Wife, a careful, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate and tender-hearted Mother, a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41864:26"/> compaſſionate and beneficent friend;</hi> and, in all theſe reſpects and many more, <hi>a moſt exemplary Chriſtian.</hi> And then.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To complete the Character, her <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Perſeverance</hi> were no leſs eminent than her <hi>care</hi> and <hi>diligence, in well-doing.</hi> She was not only unweari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly active and conſtant <hi>in doing,</hi> but eminently ſubmiſſive and patient <hi>in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the Will of her heavenly Father.</hi> And therefore under all her painful and frequently renewed Exerciſes and Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, which indeed were very grievous, (eſpecially for the laſt twelve Months of her Life,) ſhe did with unrepining ſubmiſſion, and as much chearfulneſs as was conſiſtent with her acute pains, bow to the <hi>Soveraign diſpoſing hand</hi> of God; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning her Will to his ſo as never to have been heard all the time <hi>to charge him fooliſhly</hi> in any the leaſt murmuring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt him under what in his paternal wiſdom he ſaw meet to lay upon her. Yea in the very midſt of her wearineſs and pain when <hi>her eyes have</hi> been <hi>held waking,</hi> and her <hi>ſleep hath fled from her,</hi> ſhe would often expreſs the grateful ſenſe which ſhe had of the ſingular <hi>Mercy</hi> of God towards her,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41864:27"/> in the many inſtances wherein it pleaſed him to intermix it with her <hi>Affliction:</hi> Conſidering how much better it was with her, under her ſevereſt exerciſes, than with many others of Gods dear Children, who, by reaſon of their mean Circumſtances in the World, could not be furniſh'd with thoſe external helps &amp; accomodations, which by the diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Goodneſs of God ſhe enjoyed. Which ſhe would often ſpeak of with great compaſſion to others, and no leſs thankfulneſs to God upon her own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and eſpecially in the late cold and pinching ſeaſon, wherein ſuch were expoſed to very great hardſhip as had ſickneſs added to poverty. And thus the excellent <hi>Character,</hi> that the Apoſtle gives us of the Heirs of Heaven in the Text, was in every part of it eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found in her; who was indeed One <hi>who by patient continuance in well-doing ſought for glory and honour and immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> And then I may add, That,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Agreeably hereunto her <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> were for the moſt part <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>lively,</hi> (except at ſuch times as ſhe was under clouds of <hi>Melancholly</hi> ariſing from bodily diſtemper, which made all things look <hi>dark</hi> unto her while it prevailed)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41864:27"/> But moſt perceptibly did ſhe improve in their ſtrength and vigour for ſome months before the expiration of her Time; whereby ſhe did not only obtain a comfortable victory in a great degree over the <hi>Fear of Death,</hi> which had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been a very grievous exerciſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her: but was alſo greatly ſupported and encouraged under her continued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining <hi>Troubles</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi> For as there were many comfortable <hi>Words</hi> in the Holy Scriptures <hi>whereon</hi> God had <hi>cauſed her to hope,</hi> ſo by ſtrengthening and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing her <hi>Faith,</hi> he enabled her more cloſely to apply them to her ſelf, and ſo to take the comfort of them when ſhe needed it moſt. As under one of the laſt Returns of her Diſtempers, ſhe did very frequently revolve in her mind thoſe words of afflicted but believing <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 23. v. 10. <hi>When he hath try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me I ſhall come forth as gold:</hi> And God inabling her to <hi>mix that word with faith,</hi> made it both at that time and afterwards very uſeful to her. And ſo in her laſt ſickneſs, even the night before her death, after ſhe had been exerciſed with grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous pain the whole night and day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, having a ſhort interval of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe for a few moments while I was with her,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41864:28"/> I obſerved her to repeat unto her ſelf ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times with great complacency (as I apprehended from the pleaſant tone of her voice tho' but low) thoſe encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words of the devout Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 42. 8. The Lord will command his lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs in the day-time, and in the night his Song ſhall be with me, and my prayer unto the God of my life:</hi> Adding in the cloſe, <hi>Lord, thou art the God of my life, natural life, ſpiritual life, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life; and therefore my prayer is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee,</hi> After which her pain and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs again returning, ſhe grew more and more apprehenſive of her near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching diſſolution; and after a ſhort ſpace ſaid to me, as I ſtood by her bed-ſide, <hi>I have a dark valley to paſs through:</hi> Whereupon encouraging her to hope in God, I ſaid to her, <hi>The Father of lights will be with you there, and he will enlighten your darkneſs;</hi> to which ſhe very ſweetly replyed, <hi>and turn the ſhadow of Death into the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> And not long after ſhe ſpake to me (in theſe or the like words) <hi>I bleſs God I do not at all doubt my eternal Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, but it is ſome trouble to me that I have yet ſo little of the Joy of Gods Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> As at another time (which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41864:28"/> it were before or after the former I do not exactly remember) ſhe ſaid with ſome apparent Concern to a dear Friend ſtanding by, <hi>What! Come ſo near to the confines of a glorious eternity, and yet have no clearer proſpect of the glory of it!</hi> But altho' that <hi>unſpeakable and glorious Joy,</hi> which doth ſometimes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the lively exerciſes of Faith in the children of God in their laſt hours, was (as you may perceive by theſe hints) withheld from her; She was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Solid and great <hi>peace in believing;</hi> which of the two the more <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> tho' not the more <hi>delectable</hi> enjoyment: And I make no queſtion but that now ſhe hath the other alſo in a better way as well as in a greater proportion than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any had it in this World, even <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Joy in the divine preſence, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore.</hi> For <hi>faith and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> having both had <hi>their perfect work</hi> in her, ſhe is now gone to <hi>inherit the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in Eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, my Chriſtian Friends, the greateſt honour and reſpect that we can pay to her <hi>bleſſed Memory</hi> (which I hope will yet live among us) is to follow her Worthy Example, every one <hi>ſeeking for glory and honour and immortality</hi> in that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41864:29"/> way wherein ſhe ſought and hath now obtained all. Let me therefore earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommend this unto you all; (as I deſire alſo to charge it upon my ſelf) And more eſpecially to you her neareſt ſurviving Relatives, who had a greater advantage than any others by your nearneſs to her moſt exemplary courſe of life as an excellent pattern for you to imitate. And therefore as ſhe hath <hi>done worthily</hi> in <hi>ſerving God</hi> and <hi>her Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration according to his Will,</hi> and now <note place="margin">Rev. 14. v. 13. Heb. 4. v. 9.</note> 
               <hi>reſts from her labours</hi> in that everlaſting <hi>Sabbatiſm</hi> which <hi>remaineth for the People of God;</hi> (into which ſhe entred on the cloſe of that day of the week, which is not unfitly called by us the Chriſtian Sabbath.) Let it be your care every one to do likewiſe.</p>
            <p>And more particularly let me addreſs my ſelf unto you her hopeful Off-ſpring, her dear Children (for whom ſhe put up many a Prayer to God that he would make you all his Children.) And let me earneſtly exhort you never to forget what a Mother you had; what excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and wholeſome counſel ſhe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten gave you; and what a teaching Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſhe ſet before you, by which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now dead ſhe yet ſpeaks to you:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41864:29"/> And ſurely it is your great Concern, as you love your ſouls, to hearken to the <hi>Voice</hi> &amp; to underſtand the <hi>Language</hi> of it. There are ſome things which Actions do ſpeak out louder than any Verbal Expreſſions; and certainly if you have the heart attentively to conſider and underſtand it, you cannot be unapprehenſive that your Mothers Example calls aloud upon you all to mind the great Concernments of your Souls with ſerious care and diligence as ſhe did; to get your thoughts and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections abſtracted and drawn off from this World, and fixedly <hi>ſet upon things above,</hi> as hers were; to be diligent and induſtrious in the careful and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious performance of all Chriſtian Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, both relative and perſonal, as ſhe was; to be conſtant and ſerious in attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon Ordinances, there ſeeking the appointed food of your Souls, where ſhe both often ſought and found it; to dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſome part of your Pretious Time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day to reading the Scriptures and other good Books, devout Meditation, and ſecret Prayer, which you know was her conſtant Courſe as long as her health and ſtrength would permit; in a word, to make ſerious Religion your main bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, as it was moſt manifeſtly hers:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41864:30"/> And if you will hearken to this Call in conjunction with the Calls of GOD's Word, and that Monitory Providence that you are now under, ſo as heedfully to tread in your pious Mothers ſteps, as <hi>Dear Children</hi> following her in thoſe things wherein ſhew was a <hi>follower of God,</hi> and perſiſting in this Courſe to the end of your Life: Then let me tell you for your Comfort, that altho' Death hath at preſent made a ſeparation between her and you, it ſhall be but for a ſhort ſeaſon; and then you ſhall again live together in the glorious and bright Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Heaven, and in the beatifick Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Fruition of God and Chriſt, for ever and ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41864:30"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Funeral Sermon.</hi> By <hi>Robert Fleming,</hi> V. D. M. Preach'd in the Afternoon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. vii. 1.</bibl>
               <q>—Better is <hi>the Day of Death, than the Day of ones Birth.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS all the <hi>Faculties</hi> of <hi>Mans Soul</hi> are become miſerably depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and corrupted by reaſon of <hi>Sin:</hi> So in particular the leading and directive Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Mind</hi> or Intellect is ſignally ſo. For beſides the <hi>blindneſs</hi> and ignorance of men in things <hi>natural,</hi> there is nothing more apparent, than that univerſal <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and ſtupidity which they are under, as to their apprehenſions of things <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>eternal.</hi> For altho' there ſeems to be remanent upon the minds of all men naturally ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41864:31"/> 
               <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dera</hi> of the true impreſſions of good and evil, and ſome ſecret Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a <hi>ſoveraign Being,</hi> to which all things owe their <hi>original</hi> and <hi>continuance;</hi> yet alas, what ſad Conceptions do men entertain of things of an immaterial and and ſpiritual nature; as appears not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the <hi>Writings</hi> of the more learned and ingenious <hi>Heathens,</hi> but from innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable and dayly <hi>Inſtances</hi> even in the midſt of the Meridian Light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: So that conſtant <hi>Experience</hi> doth, in this matter, ſufficiently confirm <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Teſtimony,</hi> that <hi>the natural man knows not the things of the Spirit of God,</hi> as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring a <hi>ſubjective</hi> as well as <hi>objective ſpiritual Light</hi> to diſcern them by.</p>
            <p>However, this is <hi>one</hi> of God's <hi>ends</hi> in <hi>Revealing</hi> his <hi>Word</hi> to us, that we may (thorow his Bleſſing upon pains and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry) attain to <hi>rectified Notions and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeas</hi> of things ſo excellent in themſelves, and ſo momentous to be rightly known by us. And, as this is the <hi>ſcope</hi> of the whole <hi>Scripture,</hi> to bring <hi>Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality</hi> to <hi>Light</hi> unto us; ſo particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of this <hi>Book</hi> of the wiſe and in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive <hi>Solomon;</hi> who having undertaken a <hi>ſpeculative Journey</hi> into all the <hi>Regions</hi> of <hi>ſublunary Enjoyments,</hi> returns an experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41864:31"/> 
               <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> or <hi>Preachers</hi> of thoſe things that he thought might be of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal uſe to be known. And therefore having rubbed off the <hi>fine Varniſh</hi> and <hi>gaudy Paint</hi> of Earthly <hi>Objects,</hi> (with which they inſinuate themſelves at firſt view as beautified to our vain <hi>imiginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;)</hi> he here repreſents them impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as they are in their own natures and uſefulneſs to us.</p>
            <p>Of this we might adduce many <hi>inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> if need were: But we go no farther than the Words before us; wherein we may obſerve a Rectification of a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Miſtake,</hi> that we are apt to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. For, firſt, whereas men uſually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>Riches</hi> to a good <hi>Name;</hi> we are here inſtructed that a <hi>good Name is better,</hi> &amp; more valuable, <hi>than precious ointment,</hi> i. e. than the <hi>fatneſs</hi> of the world, and the affluence of all earthly wealth and rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. For thus I take the word, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. 1. (which ſeems to be a comment on this, or a plain account of what is here figuratively imported) For <hi>precious ointment</hi> was eſteemed of old amongſt the moſt valuable things of the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> as we ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 39. 2. And hence it is, that <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 30. A good name is ſaid to make the bones ſat.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:41864:32"/>
            <p>And, again, whereas Men generally prefer <hi>Life</hi> to <hi>Death; Solomon</hi> here tells us, that we are greatly miſtaken in the <hi>Caſe;</hi> for, that, upon the contrary, <hi>the day of Death</hi> is much to be prefer'd to <hi>the day of ones Birth.</hi> According to which <hi>Poſition,</hi> he goes on to ſhew that the houſe of <hi>Mourning</hi> is better than the houſe of <hi>Feaſting,</hi> and <hi>ſorrow</hi> preferable to <hi>Laughter,</hi> v. 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the <hi>ſecond</hi> of theſe only, that I am directed to conſider at this time, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the day of Death is better than the day of ones Birth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſtrange <hi>Paradox!</hi> and enough to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze the minds and thoughts of all ſuch as mind earthly things, and who have not attained to have their interior <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſpiritually exerciſed to diſcern ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things. Nay I am apt to think, that many even ſerious <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may find it difficult to reconcile their thoughts to this <hi>Doctrine.</hi> And therefore, on all hands, I foreſee <hi>Objections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What! (will the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripturiſt</hi> ſay) is it better not to be than to be?</p>
            <p>Is it poſſible (will the carnal <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher</hi> and <hi>Rationaliſt</hi> object) that the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41864:32"/> 
               <hi>deſtruction</hi> of nature it ſelf ſhould be preferable to its <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay even many <hi>poor Chriſtians</hi> will be ready to tell me; that it ſeems very ſtrange to them to prefer <hi>Death,</hi> which owes its Original to Sin, and is <hi>our enemy,</hi> and the <hi>laſt to be deſtroyed,</hi> to prefer (I ſay) this to <hi>Life</hi> it ſelf, wherein we have opportunity to ſerve God, and do good to our ſelves and others.</p>
            <p>And methinks I hear a multitude cry out at the hearing of this (and many ſuch <hi>Worldlings</hi> there are) What! Death better than Life: Here's ſtrange Doctrine indeed! What! Leave all our Earthly <hi>Comforts,</hi> Friends and Poſſeſſions; and that for Death and the Grave: who can have Faith to believe ſuch Doctrine as this?</p>
            <p>Well <hi>Friends,</hi> here's that which may ſilence all your <hi>Doubts,</hi> and anſwer all your <hi>Queſtions</hi> as to this matter, if you will give ear to God himſelf; that Death is preferable to Birth. But I muſt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede the ſatisfying you, as to your parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Scruples</hi> in this matter, till I ſhall have come to the <hi>Improvement</hi> of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> which I muſt now (leſt I act pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterouſly)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41864:33"/> previouſly inquire into.</p>
            <p>And here, though the Words are in themſelves ſo very plain, that I ſee no momentous Variation among <hi>Criticks</hi> in the tranſlating of them: Yet I find ſome conſiderable difference in the Sentiments of <hi>Expoſitors,</hi> as to the meaning of them. For ſome underſtand the Text of all Mankind, with reſpect only to this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life,</hi> laying aſide all Conſideration of the <hi>future State;</hi> as many Paſſages in this Book are undoubtedly to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. And if ſo, then the meaning on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is; That if <hi>We conſider the Vanities and Miſeries of Mankind in this World (ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting from the future) it is better to go out of it by Death, than come into it by Birth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But others underſtand it rather, as <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> referring <hi>to the death of good men,</hi> who are thereby not only <hi>freed</hi> from troubles here, but <hi>inſtated</hi> in true happineſs &amp; feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city hereafter. And this ſenſe, as it appears more conſonant to the tenour of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Truth and Phraſeology;</hi> ſo likewiſe ſeems not obſcurely to be hinted here, from its cloſe connexion with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding part of the <hi>Verſe.</hi> For it is the death of <hi>him</hi> that has a <hi>good Name,</hi> that ſeems to be here ſpoken of, and whoſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41864:33"/> Death is juſtly preferred to his Birth: For a good Name does unqueſtionably <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> true <hi>worth</hi> and vertue, as its <hi>Foundation</hi> and Baſis. And tho' the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet of <hi>good</hi> be not expreſſed in the Hebrew, but ſimply <hi>a name,</hi> which is preferred to <hi>precious ointment:</hi> Yet that is ſo far from leſſening the ſenſe, that it expreſſe it with the greater Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis; as inſinuating, that wicked men have <hi>no name at all,</hi> properly ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>It is chiefly in this <hi>ſenſe,</hi> that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the proper meaning and ſcope of the words to lye; tho' I would not to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally exclude the <hi>former,</hi> by reaſon of the largeneſs of the expreſſion: for I think Scripture is to be underſtood in the largeſt ſenſe, where the words and ſcope will naturally bear it, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſion and ſtraining. And therefore the <hi>Doctrinal Propoſition</hi> that I here lay down, as the <hi>foundation</hi> of my enſuing <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> is this;
<q>
                  <hi>That as the day of Death is prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable to the day of ones Birth, with reſpect to all; when the paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel is only in reference to this Life, conſidered as miſerable, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41864:34"/> from the Future: So far more is the day of death preferable to the day of ones Birth, with reſpect to the Saints; when the parallel is not only in reference to This Life, but incluſive alſo of the Future.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In which General Propoſition, as we may ſee <hi>both ſenſes</hi> of the Text <hi>conjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> as being no way oppoſite, diſſonant, or excluſive the one of the other: So we may obſerve them <hi>ſo conjoyned,</hi> as notwithſtanding to <hi>remain Diſtinct.</hi> And therefore we muſt of neceſſity disjoyn them again in order to a diſtinct hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. And though it is the <hi>ſecond ſenſe</hi> of the words, that I principally intend to conſider and proſecute: Yet, ſince it may be of uſe to premiſe ſome <hi>brief Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> upon the <hi>former;</hi> I ſhall therefore diſtinctly and apart propoſe both ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in <hi>two Propoſitions;</hi> which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the <hi>two parts</hi> of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding General Doctrine.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>Firſt Propoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Day of <hi>Death</hi> is preferable to the Day of ones <hi>Birth,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>All;</hi> when the parallel is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in reference to this <hi>Life,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41864:34"/> as miſerable, abſtracting from the <hi>Future.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I ſuppoſe there is none that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and ſeriouſly ponders this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, but will eaſily aſſent unto it; ſince I do not here <hi>barely</hi> and nakedly <hi>reflect</hi> on the <hi>notions</hi> of Birth &amp; Death <hi>in themſelves,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Life ſimply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered;</hi> but only draw the parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them with reſpect to <hi>Life as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable,</hi> or (to ſpeak plainly) with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>the miſerys of Life.</hi> And I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe none can duely conſider this; but muſt inſtantly be enforced to prefer the <hi>exit</hi> from <hi>Miſery,</hi> to the <hi>intrat</hi> into it: Which is all that, (according to this ſenſe of the Text,) is underſtood by <hi>Death and Birth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For let us but ſuppoſe, that we were under a neceſſity to go a dangerous, tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and afflictive <hi>Journey,</hi> wherein we were to encounter with all manner of <hi>Miſeries,</hi> pains and troubles; and it were then propoſed to us, <hi>Whether we did not prefer the End and Cloſe of it, to the Beginning of it, and our Entry upon it?</hi> I reaſonably conclude (abſtracting from all conſideration of the <hi>place</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Journey might lead us,) that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41864:35"/> our Anſwer would be in the <hi>Affirmative;</hi> from the Melancholly Idea and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of ſuch a <hi>Journey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, what elſe is our <hi>Life,</hi> in this Miſerable world, but ſuch a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and afflictive <hi>Peregrination:</hi> For we are born to trouble, as the ſparks flie upward. No ſooner do we enter by <hi>birth</hi> into the <hi>Society</hi> of the <hi>Living,</hi> but our <hi>Infant Crys</hi> and Tears become a <hi>ſad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude</hi> to a ſucceeding <hi>ſorrowful ſcene.</hi> Our Childhood and Youth are wholly vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſpent in ſuch a way, as we ſeem rather to <hi>breath</hi> than <hi>live:</hi> And our propenſity then to extravagancy and ſin oblige our beſt Friends to keep us under the <hi>Pedagogy</hi> of <hi>neceſſary,</hi> tho' to us <hi>afflictive, Correction.</hi> And when ever we arrive to ſomething of further <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity</hi> and judgment, we are immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately beſet with cares and incumberances, the inſeparable <hi>Companions</hi> of worldly <hi>Buſineſs:</hi> Then do our hearts run out impetuouſly after the <hi>Trifles</hi> of time, the nick-nam'd <hi>Honours, Profits and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> thereof; the <hi>Game</hi> which <hi>Ambitious, Covetous and Wanton Spirits</hi> flie at. The fine <hi>varniſh</hi> and gaudy <hi>ſhew</hi> of guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>droſs and dung</hi> takes us; and after it are our endeavours bent. Here,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41864:35"/> 
                  <hi>cares</hi> to <hi>get</hi> this worlds <hi>droſs,</hi> cares to <hi>keep it,</hi> cares to <hi>encreaſe</hi> it, and cares to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of it, eat out the beſt part of our little time. And yet (notwithſtanding our <hi>riſing up early, ſitting up late and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bread of ſorrows,)</hi> the <hi>defective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the <hi>creature,</hi> and its <hi>tranſitori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> thwarts our hopes and expectations. Beſides, that oft a <hi>ſecret curſe</hi> from God blaſts our <hi>endeavours,</hi> and breaks our <hi>meaſures</hi> in all that we do. <hi>Riches and Eſtates take to themſelves wings and flie away as an Eagle towards Heaven,</hi> to receive a new <hi>diſpoſal:</hi> And the fair <hi>image</hi> and ſhadow of Honour, Grandeur and Pleaſure paſſeth away and leaves our minds perplexed and troubled for the diſappointment. Thus do <hi>we ſeek for the living among the dead,</hi> and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and contentment where it is not to be found. <hi>Diſtance</hi> and ſeparation from our <hi>beſt Friends</hi> eat out the <hi>ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing comfort</hi> we might enjoy in their <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Wants, pains, ſickneſs, ſorrows, fears and diſappointments</hi> ſwallow up any <hi>little pleaſure</hi> that we meet with in the world, and drown the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments otherwiſe comfortable. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all theſe things that happen to our ſelves immediately; we are oftimes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41864:36"/> to be ſad <hi>ſpectators</hi> of the many <hi>Tragedies</hi> acted in the world. We ſee <hi>National and Church Calamities, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and Perſonal Diſtreſſes:</hi> And oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the nearneſs of our Relation to others obliges us, by ſomething more than <hi>Sympathy,</hi> to ſuffer with them.</p>
               <p>And now, all theſe things being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially reflected on; if we <hi>return</hi> with <hi>Solomon</hi> (ch. 4. 1, 2, 3.) and <hi>conſider the oppreſſions that are done under the ſun,</hi> and how deſtitute, not only the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,</hi> but the <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> alſo, are of True comfort, on that account: I ſay, conſidering theſe things we may ſee ground with him <hi>to praiſe the Dead, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Living; yea to conclude that better is he than both theſe, who hath not yet been, becauſe he hath not ſeen the evil work which is done under the ſun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> How can we prefer Death to Birth and conſequently to Life? Since even <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf ch. 9. v. 4, 5. Doth plainly give the preference to Life; <hi>for a living Dog is better</hi> (ſays he) <hi>than a Dead</hi> Lion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not ſtrange or uncommon, for one and the ſame thing to come under <hi>different conſiderations</hi> at ſome times: And when it does ſo, it may be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41864:36"/> very proper accordingly to deduce quite <hi>different,</hi> yea and <hi>oppoſite,</hi> concluſions from thence. And therefore it needs not ſeem ſtrange that <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>Life,</hi> in ch. 9. in another <hi>Dialect,</hi> than he does here in my <hi>Text:</hi> Since he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects here and there upon the ſame things under quite different <hi>conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> For 1. in ch. 9. he compares Life and Death in their own <hi>natures;</hi> and therefore hath all the reaſon in the world to give the preference to <hi>Life,</hi> as being ſo illuſtrious an effect of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom and Power. But here <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> doth not compare theſe Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites <hi>in themſelves,</hi> but in an <hi>accidental conſideration</hi> only, with reference to the <hi>troubles</hi> and miſeries our Lives here are expoſed to, by reaſon of ſin: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore makes ſuch an Inference hence, as we have explained. 2. <hi>Solomon</hi> in ch. 9. does not only conſider Life <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> but <hi>under the Notion</hi> alſo, of being the <hi>way and means,</hi> thorow the right improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof men may attain to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs hereafter: Whereas thoſe that are dead are put out of <hi>capacity</hi> of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing further for their Soul. For, ſays he, <hi>to him that is joyned to the living there is hope; but the dead have no</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41864:37"/> 
                  <hi>more portion in any thing that is done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun.</hi> Which therefore ſeems to be nothing elſe, but that which he more clearly unfolds, v. 10. <hi>Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thy hand findeth to do, do it with all thy might, becauſe there is no work,</hi> &amp;c. But now in <hi>this place</hi> Solomon ſpeaks of life, <hi>abſtracting</hi> from its <hi>relation</hi> and uſe this way, and conſiders it meerly in <hi>reference</hi> to its <hi>miſeries</hi> and troubles: And therefore his Inference here, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what natively reſults from ſuch a conſideration thereof. 3. <hi>Solomon</hi> in the 9th ch. ſeems to me to ſpeak of Life and Death with <hi>reſpect</hi> to <hi>wicked men</hi> chiefly, if not only: And in this reſpect, it is certain, Life is far prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to Death; ſince (as he ſays, v. 10.) There is no <hi>preparation work</hi> to be done after death for the good of the Soul; whereas whilſt there is life there is ſtill hope that wicked men may repent and reform, before it be too late; as he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates v. 4. and according to the old ſaying, <hi>Sperandum eſt vivis, non eſt ſpes ulla ſepultis.</hi> But now (as was ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) it ſeems not obſcurely to be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here; that we are to underſtand the words of my Text, as refering, if not only, yet ſpecially to the <hi>Saints,</hi> who
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41864:37"/> thorow grace and holineſs, have attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed worthily to deſerve a good name. And this leads me to a <hi>Tranſition</hi> from the <hi>firſt</hi> to the <hi>ſecond</hi> and (as I judge) <hi>more native Meaning</hi> of the words, which I lay down to be diſtinctly conſidered in the following <hi>Theſis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>Second Propoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Day of</hi> Death <hi>is far preferable to the Day of ones</hi> Birth, <hi>with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the</hi> Saints; <hi>when the paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel is not only in reference to this</hi> Life, <hi>but incluſive alſo of the</hi> Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</head>
               <p>I don't ſay, that at <hi>all times</hi> and upon <hi>all accounts</hi> the day of Death is <hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> to be prefered to the day of <hi>Birth</hi> and to <hi>Life:</hi> Since ſometimes it may be our <hi>duty</hi> to chuſe Life before Death. For even <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, after a ſtruggle with himſelf on this account, whether he ſhould prefer death or life, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. 24. having impartially weighed the reaſons on both ſides, concludes v. 25. <hi>That conſidering the uſefulneſs of his life to the Church on earth, it was for the preſent to be preferred to death.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:41864:38"/>
               <p>Neither do I ſay here, that the Saints <hi>attain</hi> always to <hi>prefer</hi> death to life. No, alas; there are but few compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively that get this length. Even an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> will <hi>weep ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re</hi> at the thoughts of death, and <hi>chatter like a crane or ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and mourn as a dove on that account,</hi> Iſa. 38. 3, 14. And a <hi>David</hi> alſo will on this account at ſometimes be made to cry out. <hi>Pſal. 39. 13. O ſpare me that I may recover ſtrength,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But that which I <hi>aſſert</hi> here in the Propoſition laid down, is; <hi>That the Death of a Saint is preferable to his Birth, becauſe of the miſery of this preſent Life, and the happineſs of the Life to come.</hi> For if, (as we ſhewed before) death be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable to birth, <hi>meerly</hi> becauſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this life are ſo over-ballanced and weighed down by the ſorrows of time: Then ſurely the <hi>concluſion</hi> is <hi>much more</hi> ſtrong, when we conſider the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and happineſs of the <hi>future Life,</hi> and lay it alſo in the <hi>ſcale</hi> over and above. For who then can withſtand the force of this Truth; that the <hi>entry</hi> upon <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</hi> which is by <hi>Death,</hi> is much to be preferred to the <hi>entry</hi> upon a <hi>miſerable life</hi> here, which is by <hi>Birth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, as this Propoſition ſo expreſly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41864:38"/> Aſſerted in the Text, thus explained, ſeems ſo clear in it ſelf: So a more diſtinct conſideration of things, will put it beyond all further doubt and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy. And therefore I came now to <hi>Prove</hi> the Point further. Which being done, I ſhall proceed to <hi>Improve</hi> it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="proof">
               <head>The Proof.</head>
               <p>And now to Prove this Point, I ſhall endeavour to do it by ſhewing the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferableneſs of the one to the other, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account given; and that in two things: <hi>viz.</hi> 1. By explaining the <hi>Terms</hi> here uſed of <hi>Birth and Death;</hi> 2. By conſidering more <hi>directly</hi> the <hi>Preſent and Future Life,</hi> that theſe <hi>two Periods</hi> of <hi>Birth and Death</hi> enter the <hi>Saints</hi> upon.</p>
               <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> I ſhall briefly reflect upon the Terms of Birth and Death. And here, (as in many other things) I find a <hi>lameneſs</hi> and defectiveneſs in <hi>Words,</hi> by which the <hi>true Notions</hi> of <hi>Things</hi> are often <hi>clouded</hi> and almoſt <hi>loſt.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, tho' I take not upon me to <hi>recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> theſe <hi>terms</hi> as <hi>vulgarly uſed:</hi> Yet the preſent <hi>ſubject</hi> neceſſarily leads me to ſome <hi>rectification</hi> of the <hi>notions</hi> of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41864:39"/> 
                  <hi>things themſelves,</hi> which we have it may be from education too eaſily imbibꝰd. For if in <hi>ordinary converſe</hi> it be a <hi>Rule, quod loquendum cum Vulgo;</hi> I think we may well ſubjoyn in <hi>ſerious Inquiries</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>things, quod ſentiendum cum D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctis.</hi> And tho' I pretend not to ſuch rectified notions of things, as others may have reacht; yet ſince this falls in my way, it may not be amiſs to conſider what <hi>eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> we are to make of <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> with reſpect to a <hi>Saint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And (1) as to <hi>Birth;</hi> tho' we muſt conſider a <hi>Saint</hi> (as all other men) to be made up of a <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> as his two <hi>conſtituent parts:</hi> Yet it is the <hi>Soul</hi> which chiefly denominates the man. Whence it is that in Scripture our <hi>bodies</hi> are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our <hi>Tents</hi> or <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> wherein we lodge for a time; ſo that, tho' the Body be indeed an <hi>Eſſential</hi> part of man, yet it is the <hi>leſs principal</hi> part; ſince the Soul can act and live as well out of it as in it. And therefore it is from the <hi>Original</hi> of the Soul, that the <hi>birth</hi> of man is chiefly to be reckoned, rather than from the <hi>formation</hi> of the body. Now if accordingly we compute the birth of a Saint; we are led to a Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Birth which reſults from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41864:39"/>
               <p>The 1ſt. is <hi>by Creation,</hi> when the Soul of Man is at firſt <hi>created</hi> and placed in the body: Which indeed carries along with it the formation of the body alſo; for we can't conceive the body to be <hi>formed</hi> as to its due perfection, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>union</hi> with the Soul, till the moment of the <hi>Souls infuſion therein;</hi> if, with the <hi>Schools,</hi> I may be admitted to uſe ſuch a word, who tell us of the Soul, that <hi>creando infunditur, &amp; inſundendo creatur.</hi> But that the Soul derives its <hi>original</hi> from Gods <hi>immediate creating it,</hi> and not <hi>ex traduce</hi> (I ſpeak with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to learned and worthy Perſons of another judgment,) may ſeem plain, if it were but from that one Scripture, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. 1. eſpecially if we duely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider its connexion with what precedes. I ſay then, that the firſt birth of man, to ſpeak properly, is to be reckoned from the union of the Soul and body in the womb; (which as to <hi>priority of time</hi> ſeems to be inſtantaneouſly upon the Creation of the Soul;) rather than from the <hi>Egreſs</hi> of the child from thence. But ſince we are moſt taken with what is moſt ſenſible to us; I ſhall not contend about words, if the thing be underſtood: Eſpecially ſeeing the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41864:40"/> Scripture is ſo calculated in its Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as to uſe words commonly in uſe, &amp; underſtood by the loweſt form of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Only (howſoever we uſe words) I am confident to ſay, that the <hi>Birth</hi> of Man may very well be reckoned from the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of Soul and Body in the womb: For <hi>whatever</hi> hath theſe <hi>two conſtituent parts</hi> of man, can be aſſign'd to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>claſs</hi> but that of <hi>Mankind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 2. Birth of Man, according to the Soul, is in <hi>Regeneration</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: Of which Chriſt ſpeaking <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. Calls it the birth of a man <hi>from above,</hi> v. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The 3. Birth is in <hi>Glorification.</hi> And this admits of a <hi>Twofold Period,</hi> viz. 1. As to the <hi>Soul only</hi> at <hi>Death,</hi> when it ſeparates from the Body, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes from that moment perfectly freed from ſin and miſery, and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the enjoyment of true happineſs above: For <hi>the Souls of juſt perſons</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then are ſaid to be <hi>made perfect,</hi> Heb. 12. 23. 2. As to <hi>Soul and Body,</hi> when <hi>re-united,</hi> at the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> which is called the <hi>Adoption and Redemption of the Body,</hi> Rom. 8. 23.</p>
               <p>Now from all this, we may arrive to make ſome tolerable <hi>Eſtimate</hi> of that which we commonly call the Birth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41864:40"/> and Death of a <hi>Saint.</hi> For 1. that which we commonly call <hi>Birth,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but <hi>mans Egreſs</hi> from the womb, and <hi>his Ingreſs</hi> into the <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Mortals</hi> here. Now what is this, but <hi>a kind of Death;</hi> ſince we, being our ſelves Mortal, ſee and converſe only with Mortal Objects, as all things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal here are. Whence it is, that all mans time on earth, even from the <hi>Evening</hi> of the <hi>Worlds Creation</hi> to the <hi>Morning of the Reſurrection,</hi> is eſteemed but as one Night; as is imported <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 14. When the Reſurrection is Emphatically Termed <hi>the Morning,</hi> both with reſpect to <hi>the night of time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding,</hi> and <hi>the day of eternity about to ſucceed:</hi> And hence alſo our Life on earth, is called <hi>a Sleep,</hi> wherein we ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>dream</hi> of things than really appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them; and out of which we are firſt thorowly <hi>awaked</hi> by Death: We may ſee this plainly hinted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 15. Whereas 2. that which we call com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly <hi>Death,</hi> is nothing elſe but the <hi>unpinning</hi> our <hi>mortal Tabernacles,</hi> and the <hi>manumitting</hi> us, into the <hi>immortal Regions of Light, Love, and Liberty.</hi> Of which the great Saints in Scripture ſpeak no otherwiſe, than in the <hi>familiar Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:41864:41"/> of putting off a ſuit of <hi>old Apparrel</hi> for <hi>new</hi> and more glorious ones. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, <hi>a being unclothed</hi> as to the Body, <hi>and clothed upon by having Mortality ſwallowed up of Life,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 4. And <hi>Peter</hi> calls it, <hi>a putting off this his Tabernacle.</hi> 2 Eph. 1. 14.</p>
               <p>Again (2) let us conſider Death; the right notion whereof will become more facile to our apprehenſions, by what we have ſaid of Life. All therefore that I ſhall ſay of it, is, that (beſides that which we commonly call ſo) there is a <hi>Twofold Death,</hi> in a Spiritual ſenſe, which falls under conſideration here.</p>
               <p>The 1. is <hi>a Death in Sin,</hi> which is <hi>entered</hi> into at our <hi>Birth</hi> into the world: For then it is, that we come to enter upon the Stage of a ſinful world. <hi>We are ſhapen in ſin and conceived in iniquity:</hi> And our Birth into the world is rather <hi>a kind of Death</hi> than <hi>Life;</hi> ſince we are <hi>expoſed</hi> thereby to <hi>ſinning and ſuffering, to vanity and vexation of Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 2. is <hi>a Death to Sin;</hi> which is <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered</hi> upon at the <hi>diſſolution</hi> of the tye between Soul and body; upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it is called <hi>Death.</hi> But, tho' it diſunite ſoul and body for a time; yet it may rather be called the Birth of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41864:41"/> 
                  <hi>Soul,</hi> in as far as it <hi>tranſlates</hi> it from all manner of <hi>ſin and miſery.</hi> It is true indeed (as was ſaid before) <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi> is a kind of <hi>new Birth</hi> to the Soul, in as far, as it delivers us from the death of ſin in a great meaſure. Yet, ſince that is but a deliverance <hi>in part;</hi> therefore it is by death only that we come <hi>totally</hi> to dye to ſin. Tho' I grant that this death to ſin comes to be <hi>more illuſtriouſly diſplay'd</hi> at the great period of the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> When the <hi>laſt enemy Death comes to be Totally deſtroyed and ſwallowed up in Victory.</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 54. So that from hence we may ſee, that <hi>our Birth into this world, is a Death in Sin:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as our <hi>Diſſolution,</hi> or <hi>the ſeparation of ſoul and body is properly a Death to Sin;</hi> or a manumiſſion and freedom given us both from Sin and miſery.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, from all that hath been ſaid in the <hi>Premiſes,</hi> as to both theſe <hi>Terms</hi> of <hi>Birth and Death;</hi> we may not injuſtly <hi>invert</hi> the notion of them, with reſpect to the <hi>Saints;</hi> and ſay, <hi>That the day of our Birth into this world, was the day of our Death, in ſin, ignorance, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and miſery: Whereas the day of our Death, may be juſtly reputed to be the day</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:41864:42"/> 
                  <hi>of our Birth, into the world of purity, knowledge, light and reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>2dly.</hi> I come now to conſider what that thing we call <hi>Life</hi> is, which the two <hi>Periods</hi> of Birth and Death enter us upon, and with reſpect to which we can only paſs a right judgement of the preferableneſs of either of them: And truely as to this matter, we are very much in the dark, taking that to be <hi>life</hi> which hath little more of it, than the very ſhew and appearance. <hi>Life</hi> is a more <hi>noble thing</hi> than we imagin, when conſidered in its <hi>right notion and idea.</hi> We talk of a <hi>vegetative</hi> and <hi>ſenſitive Life.</hi> But if in <hi>Philoſophy</hi> theſe muſt needs creep in as diſtinct ſpecies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Yet <hi>Divinity</hi> will refine our thoughts of it a little further. For ſince <hi>Life</hi> is one of the glorious <hi>Attributes</hi> of the <hi>ſupreme Being,</hi> who deſigns himſelf oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>the Living God,</hi> we muſt needs conceive ſomthing high and ſublime therein. And as God is <hi>the fountain</hi> of all Life to <hi>others,</hi> ſo it is only <hi>in him that We live.</hi> So that to ſpeak properly, we have <hi>no life in our ſelves,</hi> our <hi>breath being in our noſtrils,</hi> and we depending every moment on God for new <hi>ſupplies</hi> thereof. Therefore we find it the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41864:42"/> of God only to <hi>have Life in him-ſelf,</hi> yea and ſuch a Property as is only communicable to Chriſt, <hi>Joh. 5. 26. For as the Father hath Life in himſelf; ſo hath he given to the Son to have Life in himſelf.</hi> And therefore this is ſpoken of with reſpect to Chriſt, with a ſpecial mark of Obſervation, <hi>Joh. 1. 4. In him was Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I ſhall not run further than the <hi>Text,</hi> for the <hi>Ground</hi> of my <hi>notion</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi> For we may plainly perceive by the very <hi>Terms</hi> of Birth and Death in the words, <hi>that there is ſome Life here imported, with reſpect to which, as plainly and neceſſarily preſuppoſed, theſe periodical terms are made uſe of.</hi> Now this <hi>Life</hi> herein preſuppoſed muſt either be the <hi>preſent Life,</hi> or <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>to come.</hi> If it be the <hi>preſent Life,</hi> then it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that <hi>Solomon</hi> had very mean and <hi>low thoughts of it,</hi> ſince he <hi>prefers</hi> the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> of it by <hi>Death</hi> to the <hi>commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing</hi> it at firſt by <hi>Birth.</hi> And thoſe very mean thoughts which he hath of it, are a plain <hi>Indication,</hi> that it doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the noble deſignation of <hi>Life;</hi> as being rather <hi>a ſhadow</hi> thereof, than the thing it ſelf. But if it be <hi>the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Life</hi> that is here imported, then it
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41864:43"/> preſents us with <hi>a noble Idea</hi> of <hi>true Life</hi> indeed, as <hi>incluſive</hi> of <hi>true Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Felicity,</hi> and lets us ſee with what <hi>good Reaſon Death is here preferred to Birth.</hi> But tho' this <hi>laſt ſenſe</hi> gives us the faireſt <hi>proſpect</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> and the moſt ſolid <hi>ground</hi> of the wiſe <hi>Solomons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination</hi> of this caſe; yet I think, we are to include <hi>both</hi> theſe <hi>ſorts</hi> of Life as preſuppoſed clearly in the <hi>Text.</hi> For as <hi>Solomon runs</hi> the <hi>parallel</hi> expreſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Birth and Death: So his doing thus, doth manifeſtly <hi>preſuppoſe</hi> that he had run the <hi>parallel</hi> alſo between the <hi>Preſent</hi> and <hi>Future Life;</hi> for except the <hi>Periods</hi> of Birth and Death have reſpect to <hi>theſe,</hi> they muſt be reckoned to ſtand as <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> here without any ſignificancy. But, tho' it is indubitable that <hi>Solomon</hi> runs the parallel here between Life Preſent and Future: Yet we are not to imagine that he compares them, <hi>as being both included in the true notion of Life,</hi> and ſo as <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> under the ſame <hi>Genus;</hi> but rather <hi>as two Oppoſites;</hi> ſo as to conſider that which we call the <hi>preſent Life</hi> under the notion of <hi>a kind of Death or ſtate of Death;</hi> and ſo to vendicate the notion of <hi>true</hi> Life to the <hi>future</hi> only. For as I ſaid before, (when I explained the terms of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41864:43"/> Birth and Death,) that our <hi>Birth into this world,</hi> was rather our <hi>Death in Sin</hi> and Miſery: Whereas <hi>our death out of this world,</hi> is more properly <hi>our Birth into Happineſs</hi> and felicity. So I ſay now of the Preſent and Future Life; that <hi>the Preſent Life is rather the ſtate of the dead that we die into when we are born: Whereas the Future Life is that only which deſerves the name of Life, as being that ſtate that we are born into when we come to that period, which we call death.</hi> And tho' this <hi>invertion</hi> of <hi>Terms</hi> may ſeem ſtrange at firſt, to ſuch who are ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſed in ſenſe, as not to reflect on things as they are indeed in themſelves: Yet if once we come to entertain <hi>genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine conceptions of time and eternity,</hi> and what concerns theſe, we will ſee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſon for ſuch a <hi>rectification of vulgar opinions,</hi> wherein men are oft de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, contrary to reaſon it ſelf, from a <hi>miſapplication of meer words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore ſince I take Life for that which either is <hi>proper</hi> to God, or which <hi>derivatively</hi> is communicated to <hi>ſubjects capable</hi> of it, (I mean made ſo by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;) it is therefore to be laid down. as the <hi>baſis</hi> of our enſuing reflections, that <hi>Life and Happineſs</hi> are the ſame
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41864:44"/> thing, tho' the words expreſs this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently to us. But it is only the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of true <hi>Life or Perfection, as pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the Saints</hi> that I am here to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. Which, that it may the more diſtinctly appear, it may not be amiſs to run the <hi>Parallel</hi> a little between the <hi>preſent and future Life,</hi> as we call them; that we may the more eaſily admit of the <hi>Concluſion</hi> here in the <hi>Text,</hi> as to the preferableneſs of the latter to the firſt: Which methinks the Apoſtle expreſſes well; when he calls the future Life, by a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Life;</hi> aſſigning to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life the deſignation of <hi>Mortality</hi> only, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 4. And in doing this, I muſt firſt conſider what <hi>thoſe Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of Life</hi> are that <hi>denominate</hi> it <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, happy and, deſirable.</hi> And as to this, I ſhall expreſs my ſelf in words common and known to all; that the <hi>impreſſions</hi> may be the more clear and cogent. And now, as to this matter, I cannot think of any <hi>Conveniency</hi> or <hi>true Qualification of Life</hi> wanting, where theſe <hi>ſeven Things</hi> Concur; <hi>viz. 1. Perfect Health; 2. Full enjoyment of all Good; 3. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmixed and undiſturbed Peace and Joy; 4. The moſt pleaſant place of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode; 5. The moſt excellent Company;</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:41864:44"/> 6. <hi>An untainted Good Name; 7. The perpetual Duration of all theſe.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us conſider theſe <hi>Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> or Properties of Life, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect both to the <hi>Preſent</hi> and the <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> that we may ſee, whether our <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage by Birth</hi> into the one, or <hi>by death</hi> into the other be to be preferred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. <hi>Perfect Health.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>By this we underſtand <hi>perfect recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> both of <hi>Soul and body,</hi> and all the faculties and powers of them. And if ſo, our <hi>Inquiry</hi> muſt be, where this rare <hi>Jewel</hi> is to be found, without which all our other comforts are inſipid and taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
               <p>Surely it cant be acquired in <hi>this</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable <hi>World,</hi> either as to <hi>Mind or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> For as to our Minds; how <hi>unculti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated</hi> are our <hi>judgments</hi> as to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of ſpiritual things! How <hi>vain</hi> are our <hi>thoughts!</hi> How <hi>perverſe</hi> our <hi>wills!</hi> How <hi>irregular</hi> our <hi>affections!</hi> How <hi>treacherous</hi> our <hi>memories!</hi> And how <hi>lame and defective</hi> are our <hi>actions and performances,</hi> even to the moſt ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>duties.</hi> And as to our <hi>Bodies;</hi> do we not carry about with us the <hi>Principles of</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:41864:45"/> 
                  <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and the <hi>ſeeds of death</hi> it ſelf? And what innumerable <hi>pains and mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> are we here ſubject to; every day to moſt bringing along with it ſome new <hi>exerciſe</hi> or other, or at leaſt ſome <hi>tendency</hi> to it.</p>
               <p>But then, if we caſt our eyes forward upon that <hi>bleſſed ſtate</hi> that is to enſue upon the back of death; we may there ſee this invaluable bleſſing actually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. No <hi>cloud</hi> doth then offuſcate the mind and <hi>judgment;</hi> no <hi>vanity</hi> of <hi>thought,</hi> no <hi>perverſneſs</hi> of <hi>will,</hi> no <hi>irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity</hi> of <hi>affections,</hi> no <hi>treachery</hi> of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,</hi> no <hi>deficiency</hi> in <hi>duty;</hi> I ſay none of all theſe things is then preſent to <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb or corrupt</hi> the Soul. And when the great period of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> comes, <hi>perfect health</hi> will be alſo the inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>property</hi> of the <hi>Body:</hi> In order to which, it remains in the mean time in the grave, in order to <hi>purification and preparation</hi> for <hi>ſuch a ſtate;</hi> as being e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then united to Chriſt, as we ſee, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 14, 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>Full Enjoyment of Good.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>True Life is not only incluſive of <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective,</hi> but of <hi>Objective Happineſs</hi> too:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41864:45"/> And therefore there muſt not only be <hi>perfect Health</hi> conſidered in its <hi>notion,</hi> but the <hi>full Enjoyment of Good,</hi> even of all good, and the ſupreme good.</p>
               <p>But now, let us reflect ſeriouſly with our ſelves, if this be attainable here. But what! Are we not <hi>abſent from the Lord whilſt we are at home in the body?</hi> And is it poſſible that we can be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to enjoy fully true good; whilſt we are at ſuch a diſtance from the ſupreme good, God himſelf. It is true, we may enjoy here ſome taſts of Gods love and favour: But theſe are but ſome drops, compared with the ocean of felicity. Do we not here Complain, Cry and Lament, that we want this and the other good thing? We are ſtill craving and never ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied. And therefore it is ſufficiently evident that we want many things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and conducive to make our life truly happy.</p>
               <p>But, on the other hand, what can be wanting to us, when we come to <hi>enjoy God fully,</hi> who is the only <hi>neceſſary Good,</hi> the only <hi>ſuitable Good,</hi> and the <hi>All ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Good.</hi> O this <hi>bleſſed feaſt</hi> upon the <hi>hive of ſweetneſs,</hi> the <hi>ocean of pleaſure,</hi> the <hi>Treaſure of Happineſs!</hi> upon which the <hi>Celeſtial inhabitants,</hi> are ever feaſting and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41864:46"/> yet ever full. Who can conceive the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite bounty</hi> of the King of Heaven, which he there lets out, to the wonder and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhment of <hi>Angels and glorified Souls!</hi> Who can expreſs the <hi>joy,</hi> the <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> the <hi>ecſtaſie,</hi> that ſills the thoughts and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the affections of thoſe happy <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetters!</hi> All <hi>tears are now wiped away from the Saints</hi> once ſorrowful and weeping <hi>eyes.</hi> They have <hi>forgotten their former poverty, and remember their miſery no more.</hi> O bleſſed, bleſſed, ever bleſſed they, who are now got ſafe into <hi>this banquetting Houſe;</hi> and who have <hi>the banner of love</hi> diſplayed over them to the full! O how pure! How perfect! Are <hi>thoſe pleaſures which are at Gods right hand!</hi> What can be thought to be wanting to thoſe, who ſee <hi>the face of God,</hi> and <hi>the Lamb</hi> for ever, and who are admitted to <hi>eat of the tree of life, that is in the midſt of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God. They thirſt no more, but are led to the pure fountains of living water that flows from the throne of God.</hi> In a word, we may eaſily conceive, what their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and affluence of all things is, when we have ſaid, <hi>that God himſelf will be to them all in all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:41864:46"/>
               <head>3. <hi>True Peace and Joy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And now what elſe can be the reſult and effect of both <hi>ſubjective and objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive happineſs,</hi> but <hi>undiſturbed peace and unmixed joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which are ſuch bleſſings, as we have only ſome <hi>pledges</hi> and <hi>earnests</hi> of here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. For we all know, or at leaſt may know, what <hi>allays</hi> theſe admit of here; by <hi>troubles and perplexities, griefs and fears,</hi> that conſtantly attend us, and give us ſufficient reaſon to conclude that <hi>our reſt is not here.</hi> All our mirth, joy and quiet here, is fleſhly, vain, and tranſitory. Our <hi>laughter is like the crackling of thorns under a pot;</hi> and oftimes <hi>in the midſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the heart is ſorrowful, and the end thereof heavineſs.</hi> And if at any time, we are here admitted to the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods love, and the ſight of his face, as a juſt ground of peace and joy; yet how quickly do theſe remove from us, whereby our <hi>Sky</hi> becomes <hi>overcaſt</hi> again with new <hi>clouds, which return after the rain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if we caſt our eyes within the vail, we ſhall perceive true reſt, peace and joy prepared for the Saints; in ſo much, that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41864:47"/> even Heaven it ſelf is upon this account termed ſingly <hi>peace.</hi> Iſa. 57. 1, 2. Thete our praiſes ſhall be brim full with Raptures of ſatisfaction, joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4. <hi>The moſt delightful Place of Abode.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A pleaſant <hi>ſituation</hi> is that which adds much to the ſatisfaction of ones abode here; and a delightful <hi>ſeat and place</hi> to be in, is certainly one of the greateſt <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences</hi> of Life.</p>
               <p>But can any <hi>ſpot of Earth</hi> bear this Character, in a true and full ſenſe; when the very <hi>ground is curſed</hi> upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of mans ſin? No, no; we may juſtly cry out, with <hi>David,</hi> wo is me that I dwell in <hi>Meſcheſh,</hi> and in the Sun ſcorch'd <hi>Tents of Kedar.</hi> We are here only in a <hi>wilderneſs ſtate.</hi> And tho' God hath given us many eminent <hi>Inſtances</hi> of his wiſdom and power, in the admirable frame even of this lower Creation: Yet alas, all theſe are but the <hi>dark ſhadows</hi> of the <hi>glorious Lanſkip</hi> of the <hi>upper Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it is <hi>Heaven</hi> alone that can anſwer ſuch a <hi>Character,</hi> as being a <hi>place</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made for <hi>true pleaſure</hi> and delight. If
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41864:47"/> the <hi>Palace</hi> of the <hi>great God</hi> may be thought to be infinitely glorious and admirable, above the <hi>clay-cottages of thoſe whoſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation is in the duſt;</hi> then let us enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain more ſuitable thoughts of that ſo deſirable a place: Which is ſuch, as <hi>the heart of man could never conceive</hi> any thing to bear any true reſemblance unto it; the moſt magnificent repreſentation of it in Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. Being only <hi>figurative,</hi> and therefore far ſhort of what it is in it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5. <hi>The moſt Excellent Company.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>It is <hi>Society</hi> that Alleviats, in a great meaſure, our ſorrows and griefs here, and makes up the defects of other things: And as man is made for <hi>Society,</hi> ſo there is nothing more deſirable than <hi>excellent and ſuitable company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, tho' (comparatively ſpeaking) ſome ſuch may be found here; yet our beſt company on earth is, as other things, vain, and ſhort of the true Idea of ſuch a bleſſing. <hi>The beſt men are men at best,</hi> and ſubject to unruely <hi>paſſions and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours;</hi> which is a great <hi>allay</hi> unto their company: beſides that oft-times, <hi>ſins and ſcandals, miſeries and wants,</hi> render the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41864:48"/> company of men but little acceptable to one another. And if there were none of theſe things to diſturb us, yet <hi>all men are mortal,</hi> and can enjoy one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>another but for a ſhort time on earth.</p>
               <p>But then, if we turn our thoughts <hi>from earth to heaven,</hi> we find our wiſhes and deſires this way fully anſwered. For there we ſhall be admitted to converſe with the <hi>great God</hi> himſelf, the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious object of delights, and infinitely the beſt company. There we ſhall be admitted to lean our heads on <hi>Chriſts boſom,</hi> and tell him all our moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſecrets, and have him to be our dear friend and companion for ever. There we ſhall be equal to the <hi>Angels,</hi> and become their <hi>fellow-ſervants</hi> and <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-worſhippers.</hi> And there ſhall we enjoy the company of all the glorified Saints, the <hi>Patriarchs, Kings, Prieſts, Prophets, Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, Martyrs, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Miniſters and Christians, that as bright clouds of witneſſes have got to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before us.</hi> And there, among others, we ſhall meet (with <hi>endeared Embraces)</hi> our <hi>loving and dear Friends and Relatives, that were ſo acceptable to us on earth.</hi> We ſhall all meet together in the <hi>Celeſtial</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:41864:48"/> 
                  <hi>Regions,</hi> and in the <hi>ſtreets and Manſions</hi> of the <hi>new Jeruſalem:</hi> and as we ſhall be <hi>ever with the Lord,</hi> ſo ſhall we be <hi>ever</hi> alſo <hi>with one another.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6. <hi>An untainted good Name.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This is yet another bleſſing that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the <hi>true life:</hi> For to be expoſed to <hi>reproaches,</hi> and to underly <hi>calumnies</hi> and evil reports, is inconſiſtent with the notion of this; tho' I grant God can turn this, as other evils, to the advantage of his own.</p>
               <p>But alas, this is one ſuperadded miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the many that we meet with here, that we are toſſed to and fro with the various <hi>cenſures</hi> of men. Even the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves were ſo far from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaping this Contagion, that <hi>they were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as the droſs and refuſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> as the very vileſt of miſcreants, by a blind, mad world. <hi>Fame</hi> hath been for a long time <hi>the Goddeſs of ambitious and high Spirits:</hi> But it is the greateſt <hi>nonſenſe</hi> to talk of <hi>perpetuating ones name here;</hi> ſince the furtheſt that the <hi>fame</hi> of any can go, is but to the <hi>limits of time and ſpace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fame and good name</hi> then, are <hi>Jewels</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:41864:49"/> of the <hi>Eternal Crown of Happineſs,</hi> wherewith God doth adorn ſuch only as he admits to the everlaſting enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of himſelf. He then that <hi>conquers</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> hath but the <hi>ſhaddow</hi> of <hi>true Fame,</hi> which God beſtows only on ſuch who have thorow <hi>grace</hi> attained to <hi>overcome ſin, Satan and the world.</hi> And he alſo who hath left his <hi>name</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in the <hi>frontis-piece</hi> of <hi>an hundred learned Volumns,</hi> hath yet fallen ſhort of a <hi>perpetual fame;</hi> except he hath alſo attained to have his <hi>name ingraven and inrolled</hi> in the <hi>eternal Regiſters and Records of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7. <hi>The Perpetual Duration of all theſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Had we all the forementied <hi>Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of true and perfect Life;</hi> yet if we did but admit of a <hi>ſuſpition</hi> in our thoughts as to their <hi>continuance and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manency:</hi> This one ſuſpicious thought would be enough to dump all our ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction with reſpect to ſo many bleſſings. And therefore to make Life every way happy and perfect, this ſuperadded Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of the <hi>Eternity</hi> of all, muſt of neceſſity come in.</p>
               <p>And therefore we are hence led to ſee,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41864:49"/> that there is no <hi>true Life</hi> here, ſince all our <hi>comforts and enjoyments</hi> are <hi>tranſitory and fading;</hi> as being <hi>momentary and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd within the narrow limits and precincts of years, days, hours and minutes.</hi> And no wonder; ſince even that which we call <hi>Life</hi> here, <hi>is it ſelf but a vapour, that appeareth for a little, and then va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth</hi> away; yea, <hi>ſuch</hi> a vapour, as has not ſo much a <hi>being,</hi> as the <hi>ſhew</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance thereof: For to this purpoſe doth <hi>James,</hi> ch. 4. v. 14. Point it forth very expreſſively; when he ſays it is a vapour, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>But on the other hand, this adds to all the <hi>happineſs</hi> of the <hi>future Life,</hi> that all the <hi>enyoyments and bleſſings</hi> there are <hi>permanent</hi> and eternal. <hi>No ruſt doth there corrupt them, nor Thief ſteal them, nor age waſt them, nor death devour them.</hi> They that once enter upon the actual fruition of ſuch Enjoyments, do ever retain their poſſeſſion of them.</p>
               <p>And thus I have run thorow the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> of <hi>true Life,</hi> as briefly as I could. Which, ſince they only <hi>quadrate</hi> with the <hi>future Life, of perfection;</hi> I ſuppoſe it is eaſy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, what Reaſon we have to conclude with <hi>Solomon,</hi> that Death to a Saint is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41864:50"/> far preferable, on all accounts, to his Birth; or, to ſpeak it in his very words, <hi>Better is the day of ſuch a ones Death, than the day of his Birth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="improvement">
               <head>The Improvement.</head>
               <p>In the next place I come, to bring home the <hi>Doctrine</hi> to our ſelves, by a ſerious <hi>Improvement</hi> thereof: Which I deſign ſhall be <hi>Judgment,</hi> and <hi>Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of our Practice;</hi> with reſpect to our Duty, as to both.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1ſt. <hi>The Information of our Judgments.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Although all that hath been ſaid, was with this deſign to rectifie our thoughts, as to the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which is the <hi>ſubject matter</hi> of the <hi>Text:</hi> Yet there are theſe things farther that we may rationally and indeed neceſſarily <hi>Inferr</hi> hence.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Infer. <hi>We ſee</hi> (from what hath been ſaid) <hi>not only the certainty, of a Future Life and ſtate, but of an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Happineſs and Glory alſo, which the Souls of the Righteous paſs into at Death.</hi> When <hi>the poor Beggar dyed, he was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by Angels into</hi> Abraham's <hi>boſome;</hi> Luk. 16. 26. <hi>And the poor penitent</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:41864:50"/> 
                     <hi>Thief was on one and the ſame day, in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the Croſs with Chriſt, and in para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe with him.</hi> Luk. 23. 43. And St. <hi>Paul, the great Columbus of the upper world</hi> (who firſt made a voyage and returned again in time as we ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 1, 4, &amp;c.) Could never reflect afterwards upon that <hi>paradiſe,</hi> which he then ſaw, but with earneſt breathings to be there again; as we ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 1, 2. &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. And indeed if there were not a <hi>future ſtate,</hi> we could never give any rational account, why God ſhould make ſo Noble a Creature as Man; but might then cry out with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 89. 47. Wherefore haſt thou made all men in vain.</hi> And were not this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious life and ſtate to be entered upon, by the Souls of Believers, <hi>Immediately at Death,</hi> it would greatly damp the ſweet and comfortable reflections which they are called to have thereof then.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Infer. <hi>We have hence alſo a rational and ſatisfactory Anſwer to give, to all the ſcruples and Objections, that can be put up by any againſt this Doctrine.</hi> And now ſince we hinted <hi>before</hi> ſome <hi>Doubts,</hi> that naturally might ariſe in mens minds, from the <hi>firſt propoſal and idea</hi> of this Doctrine: I ſhall therefore <hi>in this place</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:41864:51"/> briefly <hi>Anſwer</hi> the ſame, from what hath been already ſaid.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore 1. Since <hi>Atheistical and Anti-ſcriptural Perſons,</hi> cry out upon this Doctrine as ridiculous, from <hi>a fond ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, that the Soul has no exiſtence when ſeparate from the body.</hi> I Anſwer, 1. That ſuch an imagination, is not only contrary to Scripture but Reaſon it ſelf. For how is it poſſible for us to conceive that ſuch a noble, active and intelligent being as the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man, ſhould be meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dependant on the body, and have only its duration for a ſhort ſpace in this vain world. Eſpecially 2. ſince we ſee, that this preſent life is rather an <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> than a <hi>reality,</hi> as all things we here converſe with are alſo.</p>
                  <p>Or, 2. If the <hi>carnal Rationaliſt and Philoſopher further object,</hi> and <hi>argue</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>this Doctrine,</hi> from the <hi>conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Deaths being the Deſtruction of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> I Anſwer, 1. that to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, there is no ſuch deſtruction of nature by Death, as many imagine. For the <hi>Soul</hi> is not deſtroyed by it; but acts and lives more nobly than before. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the <hi>Body</hi> properly deſtroyed; but only reduced into its firſt Principles, in order to be new moulded and more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41864:51"/> re-edified than before. And therefore, ſince the <hi>two Eſſential conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent parts</hi> of man remain in being; man can't be ſaid to be deſtroyed: For tho' the <hi>immediate</hi> Tye <hi>between</hi> Soul and Body be <hi>looſed,</hi> yet it is for a time only; and in the mean time <hi>the relation</hi> they ſtand in to one another continues, even when the <hi>actual union</hi> is <hi>ſuſpended.</hi> And beſides all this, it being the Soul that is principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Man; we are therefore to reckon that the man is in being ſtill, even when unbodied. But 2. let it be conſidered, that <hi>Death</hi> is not preferred to <hi>Birth or Life, meerly</hi> as it is <hi>the diſſolution of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> as <hi>now</hi> exiſting; but the <hi>formal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of this is upon the account of the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> of the future Life, which death is the paſſage into. For upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count only is it, that the Apoſtle prefers death to life, 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 4. Not for that we would be unclothed,</hi> ſays he, <hi>but clothed upon, that Mortality may be ſwallowed up of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But 3. as to what many <hi>poor ſincere-Christians</hi> are apt to object againſt this <hi>Point,</hi> from <hi>the expreſſions that ſometimes Death goes under in Scripture; of its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (as the puniſhment of ſin) <hi>our enemy, and to be deſtroyed,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 26. I
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41864:52"/> would for <hi>Anſwer,</hi> propoſe to them (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what hath been already ſaid) this one <hi>conſideration;</hi> That, tho' Death be indeed our enemy, as it is inflicted as a puniſhment of ſin, ſince the fall: Yet it has now <hi>altered</hi> its <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>end,</hi> with <hi>reſpect</hi> to <hi>Saints,</hi> ſince Chriſts death eſpecially; <hi>Chriſt having ſlain death and him that had the power thereof.</hi> Indeed <hi>Death paſſeth ſtill upon all men:</hi> but in very <hi>different reſpects.</hi> For to the <hi>wicked,</hi> death is ſtill continued as a <hi>grim Meſſenger and King of Terrours.</hi> But, as for the <hi>Saints,</hi> Death is now become Chriſts <hi>ſervant</hi> to convey home the Souls of his own to himſelf. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſaid <hi>to have aboliſhed death,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 10. So he is ſaid alſo, Rev. 1. 18. <hi>To have taken, into his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody and keeping, the Keys of Hell and Death.</hi> Upon which accounts we may perceive, what little reaſon we have to fear Death, when he acts only in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion under our dear Lord and Saviour;</hi> and when alſo ſo bleſſed a <hi>Guide</hi> as he leads the way.</p>
                  <p>And 4. As to the <hi>Objection,</hi> which the <hi>vulgar ſort of groveling Mortals</hi> are apt to make againſt Death; <hi>that it robbs them of, and ſeparates them from all their</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:41864:52"/> 
                     <hi>comforts, friends, poſſeſſions, enjoyments and hopes.</hi> I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> that where the caſe is thus with any, I muſt needs grant they have reaſon to prefer life to death. If thou haſt all <hi>thy portion in this life,</hi> I ſhall <hi>not wonder</hi> to ſee thee prefer <hi>earth to heaven,</hi> and <hi>duſt to gold.</hi> But, O poor <hi>wretch,</hi> art thou not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of ſuch an objection; which mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates indeed againſt thee, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Doctrine. For the Saints (of whom we here ſpeak) will tell thee; that, whereas <hi>death ſeparates thee</hi> from all thy <hi>comforts;</hi> it is in <hi>that way alone,</hi> that they expect to reap <hi>the full harveſt</hi> of all <hi>joy and comfort;</hi> for <hi>at the right hand of God there is fulneſs of joy, and in his preſence there are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Infer. We may ſee hence alſo, <hi>the folly and ignorance of the generality of men, as to their notions and conceptions, of Life and Death:</hi> Who ſeem to think, that all comforts are to be found only in this Life, and therefore give way to ſtrange and melancholly apprehenſions of death and what follows it. As there are many <hi>poor Creatures</hi> in the world, living in <hi>mean celles and cottages,</hi> in ſome obſcure corner; whoſe low minds (hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41864:53"/> never travelled from the ſmell of <hi>their native thatch and turff,)</hi> repreſent the <hi>world</hi> to themſelves no otherwiſe, than according to the <hi>ideas</hi> which a <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſpot of earth</hi> of a <hi>few miles circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> hath afforded them. So the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> of mankind ſeem to be ſo pre-oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied with the <hi>prejudices</hi> of <hi>ſenſe and cuſtom;</hi> as never to have ſuitably reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on thoſe things, which <hi>right Reaſon</hi> may not obſcurely conclude, from <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Premiſes,</hi> concerning the glory and excellency of the <hi>future state</hi> of <hi>the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> For if our thoughts were more inured to ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Meditations,</hi> we would diſpiſe the <hi>vanities</hi> of a <hi>fading life</hi> more; ſince we converſe here but with imaginary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and joys, tho' with too real griefs and miſeries.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2d. <hi>The Regulation of our Practiſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>As <hi>Practiſe</hi> is the end of <hi>Knowledge;</hi> ſo my <hi>deſign,</hi> in all that hath been ſaid, was to bring you to a ſincere &amp; conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>Performance</hi> of thoſe <hi>Duties,</hi> that the Doctrine handled doth call for from you: And therefore ſuffer me to lay them impartially before you, at this time.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41864:53"/> And, in doing this; ſince not only the <hi>Doctrine</hi> in it ſelf, but the preſent <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> calls for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and becoming <hi>Conſideration</hi> this way: I ſhall therefore endeavour, (with what ſuccinctneſs is convenient,) to do theſe two things here; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. to <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> the <hi>Doctrine Practically,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to that <hi>Duty,</hi> that is incumbent upon all from hence, as to the good of our Souls. 2. to <hi>Improve</hi> it alſo <hi>ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>ſad occaſion</hi> of this preſent meeting and concourſe.</p>
                  <p>And (1) I ſhall endeavour to <hi>Improve</hi> the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> in the <hi>General,</hi> ſo as may be of uſe to all of you. And what I have thus to ſay to you, I will compriſe and ſumm up in theſe three <hi>Directions</hi> or <hi>Rules.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Direct. <hi>Take heed how you carry with reſpect to your Spiritual ſtate, and Intereſt in God thorow Chriſt.</hi> Which <hi>Advice,</hi> I will take up in theſe three <hi>Parts;</hi> which I am ſure you are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned ſeriouſly to mind.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Examine and Try your ſelves if God be your Portion and Chriſt your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> What are you ſecure, whilſt you remain at uncertainties as to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter! What <hi>ground</hi> have you to believe,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41864:54"/> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>yours?</hi> Have you renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Sin, Satan, the world, and ſinful ſelf?</hi> Have you accepted Chriſt wholly in all his <hi>offices?</hi> and have you laid hold on him as your <hi>alone Saviour?</hi> Be careful, my friends, that you found not your <hi>hopes</hi> on a <hi>miſtake,</hi> and thus <hi>build</hi> on the <hi>ſand. Religion</hi> is more than a <hi>name,</hi> and <hi>Converſion</hi> more than a <hi>notion.</hi> Therefore <hi>Judge your ſelves</hi> impartially as to this matter, <hi>leſt you be judged</hi> to condemnation by God for your neglect to do ſo.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Be ſure,</hi> what ever you do, <hi>to lay the whole weight and ſtreſs of your Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the merits and righteouſneſs of Chriſt;</hi> and fancy not that your own inherent <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> muſt go <hi>Partner</hi> with the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt in the point of <hi>Juſtification;</hi> leſt thereby you impeach <hi>the all-ſufficient Merits</hi> of Chriſt of <hi>defectiveneſs,</hi> and claim the <hi>priviledge</hi> to be accounted <hi>your own Saviours.</hi> But endeavour, with the Apoſtle <hi>Phil. 3. 9. To be found in him, not having your own righteouſneſs, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſs which is of God by faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Mind the concernment of your Souls</hi>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:41864:54"/> 
                     <hi>Salvation with all earnestneſs and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence:</hi> For what <hi>profit</hi> will it be unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>you <hi>to gain the whole world, if you loſe your Souls, or what can you give in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change again for them</hi> if once they be loſt. Therefore trifle not away precious time and golden opportunities in doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or it may be things worſe than nothing; leſt you be forced at length to cry out (as the great <hi>Grotius</hi> did when dying) <hi>Ah vitam perdidi operoſe nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo.</hi> Be not ſo beſotted as to lay the ſtreſs of your hopes upon an <hi>imaginary Death-bed Repentance:</hi> But ſince now you have a price put into your hands to get wiſdom with; beg and endeavour after that happy Part and Lot, that ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be taken from you, when once at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Direct. <hi>Take heed how you carry, with reſpect to your Bodies.</hi> And as to this matter, I will give you a taſt of my <hi>Thoughts,</hi> in theſe <hi>three things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Watch againſt your Bodies, that they prove not ſnares to your Souls;</hi> as they are I fear to many in more than one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. For 1. how oft do our <hi>ſenſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and cheat the Soul, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with innumerable <hi>objects</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract and diſturb it from the purſuit
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41864:55"/> of more noble things. And 2. the <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and unruely <hi>Imagination</hi> doth no leſs oft diſcompoſe the Mind and Reaſon, by innumerable <hi>Chimera</hi>'s; in the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and producing of which it is for the moſt part ſtrangely fruitful. Yea 3. the <hi>wants</hi> of the Body prove oft-times a great <hi>Remora</hi> to the Soul in its ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual operations, by giving occaſion to ſollicitude and anxious cares, about <hi>what we ſhall eat and drink, and wherewithall we ſhall be clothed, and how we ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſuch and ſuch evils and troubles,</hi> &amp;c. In all which reſpects, we have great reaſon both to watch over and to watch againſt our Bodies.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Live above your Bodies.</hi> Let not your thoughts and cares terminate on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there. What! Shall a mortal fade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Carcaſe</hi> ſwallow up our <hi>thoughts</hi> and inhance our <hi>affections;</hi> when the time is coming, that Death will at one blow cut down the ſame, whereon we have beſtowed ſo much pains in vain? Yea the time is coming, when this beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful outſide will ſtink and turn to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: And then <hi>worms</hi> muſt neſtle in thoſe <hi>holes,</hi> where ſprightly <hi>eyes</hi> did once ſhine; and all our graceful and well proportioned <hi>members</hi> and parts
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41864:55"/> moulder down into deformity and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs. Therefore let us hence learn to live above our Bodies.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Be content to be unbodied for a time.</hi> It is this way alone that we can expect to ſee God fully, and to reach the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Life; and therefore it is our <hi>Duty</hi> to work up our hearts to an <hi>hearty contentment</hi> in and <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> with this <hi>way, method and ordinance</hi> of Gods own <hi>appointment,</hi> in order to conſummate our felicity. Nay let me ſay further, that we ought to endeavour, not only to be <hi>content to die,</hi> but to be <hi>willing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to depart that we may be with Chriſt,</hi> which is beſt of all. This was <hi>Pauls</hi> attainment, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23. And not his only, but that which was very common to the Saints in thoſe more heavenly times, <hi>Rom. 8. 23. 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 4, 5. Yea the very <hi>inanimate Creation</hi> hath an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>propenſity</hi> this way, groaning for a <hi>diſſolution</hi> as to its <hi>preſent form,</hi> that it may be reſtored to its priſtine glory and ſplendour, before it became the ſtage of ſin and theatre of miſery: This we may ſee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 19, 21, 22. Which is a conſideration that may well ſhame us out of our earthly frame, that we have ſunk into for the moſt part in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41864:56"/> theſe depraved days. I know indeed, that we are apt to reckon it a great attainment in a Chriſtian (and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively indeed with the frame of moſt it is ſo) <hi>to be content to die,</hi> (in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Divine good pleaſure) <hi>yet deſirous to live.</hi> But the excellency of the Chriſtian attainment and frame of ſpirit, in this matter, ſtands in the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> of the common order; <hi>viz. In being deſirous to die, yet content to live,</hi> in ſubmiſſion to Gods will, and in regard of ſervice to be done for God further. And indeed, when a Chriſtian hath once taſted of the pleaſure and delight of <hi>communion</hi> with God, and thus been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſome <hi>fore-taſts</hi> of the future glory, he can ſcarce any longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain himſelf <hi>(the love of God in Chriſt conſtraining him)</hi> from crying out; <hi>O Time be gone! O Eternity make haſt! Why art thou ſo long a coming to thoſe that are ready to burſt with longing after the immediate ſight and fruition of their God and Saviour forever.</hi> Don't the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and the <hi>Bride</hi> both, <hi>Eccho</hi> forth with a ſweet <hi>pathos, come Lord Jeſus:</hi> And ſhall not our Souls joyn in the conſort, and ingeminat, <hi>Amen, even ſo come Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, come, come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:41864:56"/>3. Direct. <hi>Take heed, how you carry with reſpect to your Souls.</hi> Which <hi>Advice</hi> I take up alſo in theſe <hi>Three Things;</hi> which I ſhall but very briefly propoſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt. <hi>Be careful to cultivate your Souls;</hi> that ſo you may grow dayly in a <hi>meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and preparedneſs</hi> for <hi>Heaven and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> And as there are two principal <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties</hi> of the Soul, the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Will;</hi> ſo accordingly, let it be your great ſtudy to adorn theſe, with what tends to render them more and more excellent. And 1. <hi>Improve your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, by dilating and enlarging them by further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of true &amp; ſpiritual Knowledge.</hi> Grow in the Knowledge of <hi>God and Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>the Vanity of the World</hi> and <hi>Excellency of Heaven,</hi> and of the <hi>Worth of the Soul;</hi> and in ſumm, of all <hi>Goſpel-Truths and Promiſes,</hi> and the <hi>legal Precepts and Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> that are revealed as needful to be known. 2. <hi>Improve your Wills and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections alſo, by more and more Grace;</hi> that the <hi>Habits</hi> thereof may be ſtrengthened by repeated <hi>Acts,</hi> and that ſo theſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits thus ſtrengthened, may be <hi>exerted</hi> &amp; put forth the more ſweetly and freely, in the out-going of the Soul in all its acts and operations.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:41864:57"/>2. <hi>Employ your Souls always in Gods ſervice.</hi> This is and ought to be your chief and conſtant work and buſineſs. Let us with complacency and chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imploy our ſelves this way; that it may be our <hi>meat and drink to do the will of our Father who is in Heaven.</hi> What is our buſineſs in the world if it be not this. For it is an opportunity to ſerve God here, that alone can make a Saint content and willing to ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in this <hi>Dung-hill world,</hi> when his Soul is otherwiſe wholly propending <hi>Heaven-ward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Seek to have your <hi>Souls</hi> admitted to <hi>Converſe</hi> with God here. For if we are not admitted to this happy <hi>Society</hi> wholly, yet let us endeavour after this <hi>Bleſſing</hi> here below, in as far as God may be pleaſed to priviledge us with it. Alas, that we ſhould be ſatisfied with the <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>ſhadows and vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things</hi> here below; whilſt we may have <hi>communion with the Father and his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is this bleſſed Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip alone, that can <hi>ſweeten and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliariſe Death</hi> and diſſolution to us, and make <hi>ſeparation</hi> appear <hi>rather a change of our Place than of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:41864:57"/>
                  <p>But (2) I muſt alſo ſubjoyn ſome more <hi>ſpecial improvement</hi> of the <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,</hi> with reſpect to our <hi>Practiſe</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>the ſad Occaſion</hi> of our preſent <hi>Meeting</hi> together at this time. And here (tho' what I am to ſay further may be of uſe to all, yet) I addreſs my ſelf more particularly to <hi>You,</hi> whom this <hi>Diſpenſation of Providence</hi> doth more nearly reſpect and concern. And what I have to ſay here, I ſhall compriſe in a <hi>Threefold Counſel or Advice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Counſ. <hi>Submit your ſelves cordially to Gods correcting hand in this ſtroke.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the <hi>Patience</hi> of <hi>Job,</hi> under greater <hi>ſeverity;</hi> and ſay with him, <hi>the Lord hath given, and the Lord hath taken, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> All the <hi>Providences</hi> of God are the <hi>Effects</hi> of the <hi>higheſt wiſdom,</hi> and with reſpect to the <hi>Saints,</hi> they all <hi>flow from love and mercy alſo.</hi> Nothing falls out caſually in ſuch matters, however they appear to us. For if a <hi>ſparrow fall not to the ground, without our Father which is in Heaven;</hi> then ſurely <hi>a Friend, a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and Child of God cannot be removed hence without his ſpecial providence; for are we not of more value, than many ſparrows?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Counſ. <hi>Moderate your ſorrows as</hi>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:41864:58"/> 
                     <hi>to the Perſon deceaſed,</hi> from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the <hi>place</hi> and <hi>company</hi> ſhe is gone to, and the <hi>happineſs</hi> ſhe now enjoys. For, bleſſed be God, <hi>we ſorrow not to day as thoſe that have no hope:</hi> For we have not the leaſt ſhadow of doubt as to her happineſs and glory. But if we have any thing to bewail this day, it is as to our ſelves, <hi>that we are left behind.</hi> Indeed we have reaſon to lament <hi>her removal, as a loſs to her Relatives, a loſs to her Friends, yea and a loſs to the Country.</hi> But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, with reſpect to her ſelf, we have rather cauſe of joy than ſorrow. If I may be ſo bold, as to ſuppoſe the Lord ſpeaking to us, in the words of <hi>Jerom,</hi> (who to comfort a pious <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron,</hi> named <hi>Paula,</hi> upon the death of her <hi>daughter,</hi> brings in the Lord ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her,) may we not think that the Lord ſpeaks, (by this diſpenſation) unto you to this purpoſe. <q>I have made this <hi>your Relative and Friend mine.</hi> But what! Do you envy my <hi>poſſeſſion?</hi> Where can ſhe be <hi>better</hi> than <hi>with me?</hi> Would you bring her back from <hi>Rivers of Pleaſures</hi> to the <hi>valley of Tears?</hi> From <hi>Health to Sickneſs?</hi> From <hi>a Throne to a Drageon.</hi> May we not therefore,</q>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:41864:58"/> in this caſe, allude to our Lords expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Joh. 14. 28. If ye loved me, ye would rejoyce, becauſe I go to the Father.</hi> And I ſuppoſe, could we now hear her ſpeak to us, it would be in words of ſuch an importance.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Counſ. <hi>Imitate what was Good, Valuable and Praiſe-worthy in her.</hi> Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate her, in her <hi>Faith;</hi> in her <hi>Charity;</hi> in her <hi>Aſſiduity</hi> in Religious <hi>Duties;</hi> in an impartial <hi>ſcrutiny</hi> into the ſtate of her own Soul, in her <hi>cloſet retirements,</hi> and <hi>publick walk and converſation;</hi> in a ſincere <hi>deſign</hi> to <hi>honour and pleaſe God;</hi> in a chearful <hi>delight in doing good</hi> to all; and in <hi>patience and ſubmiſſion</hi> under <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,</hi> and this Leads me to a <hi>Tranſition</hi> from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> to the <hi>Perſon;</hi> in whom we may ſee a <hi>Laudable Example,</hi> which may ſerve to back the <hi>Preceding Precepts,</hi> as being (at leaſt to many of us here) an <hi>ocular Demonſtration</hi> thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>The Character.</head>
               <p>And here give me leave to preſent you with a <hi>few hints</hi> of this <hi>worthy Saint;</hi> which I have either known from <hi>her ſelf immediately,</hi> or from an <hi>impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial obſervation of her Life and walk.</hi> And
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41864:59"/> I am the rather emboldned to do this; becauſe, although many others knew her much <hi>earlier and longer</hi> than I; yet there were <hi>few,</hi> ſhe was pleaſed to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to be more <hi>free</hi> with in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments</hi> of her <hi>Soul.</hi> But, ſince my <hi>Brother,</hi> who hath already preceded me, on the <hi>ſame occaſion,</hi> hath, beſides a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Character</hi> of her, given you ſome <hi>ſuccinct narrative</hi> of her <hi>laſt Hours;</hi> I ſhall therefore only preſent you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome account of her <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Life and Converſation,</hi> that may be of further uſe with reſpect to <hi>Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by others, as well as condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to make her <hi>Memory</hi> further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
               <p>Her <hi>natural Temper</hi> was <hi>Retired and ſerious,</hi> and altogether averſe from <hi>crouds of Company</hi> and the <hi>hurries of the world:</hi> Yet no way <hi>Moroſe and Sullen,</hi> but <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and Affable</hi> to All; and becoming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Free</hi> alſo with her <hi>Friends:</hi> And ſuch ſhe ſpecially reckoned ſo, who were truely <hi>Pious and Religious.</hi> For it might juſtly be ſaid of <hi>her,</hi> as of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> that <hi>all her delight was in the Saints, whom ſhe eſteemed the excellent Ones of the Earth.</hi> And <hi>ſuch Perſons</hi> ſhe valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the <hi>degree of worth</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:41864:59"/> that ſhe ſee in any, without <hi>regard</hi> to the <hi>diſcriminating name of a Party.</hi> For ſhe was careful, (beſides her regard for all pious and vertuous Perſons) duely to ponder the <hi>ſuper added Qualifications</hi> that ſhe ſee in any, that might entitle them to a more particular ſhare in her <hi>Friendſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as her <hi>Temper</hi> was naturally <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> ſo God bleſſed her very early, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in her <hi>childhood,</hi> with <hi>true ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Piety;</hi> as ſhe hath been forced oftner than once to confeſs, with grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Acknowledgments</hi> of Gods mercy to her on that account, as well as comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to <hi>reflect</hi> upon the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> ſhe had, in being deſcended from <hi>eminently Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Parents,</hi> and brought up in <hi>true Chriſtian Education.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A natural <hi>Modeſty</hi> attended her, in all her <hi>Actions,</hi> even the moſt ſerious. An <hi>eminent inſtance</hi> whereof was this; that, tho' ſhe was educated in <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational-way</hi> very ſtrictly, yet ſhe could never be induced, (as is uſual with ſuch,) to give any <hi>open</hi> or <hi>formal account</hi> of her Souls concerns before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and upon that account ſhe had been wholly debarred from the <hi>moſt ſpiritual of ordinances;</hi> had not God,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41864:60"/> (by providential acquaintance) impreſt that juſt Character of her upon the mind of the <hi>Reverend Dr. Jacomb,</hi> as (upon an inquiry into ſuch things) to admit of her, (notwithſtanding this) to <hi>all ordinances</hi> with <hi>intire ſatisfaction.</hi> This I ſpeak not, with the <hi>leaſt deſign</hi> to reflect on any <hi>Party or Way;</hi> (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince God hath been pleaſed of late to cement <hi>the two ſticks of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim <hi>and</hi> Judah in ſo great a meaſure, <hi>(by an happy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion:)</hi> but I mention it only, by way of <hi>Caution</hi> both to <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Churches;</hi> that we may ſee, what tenderneſs is required in <hi>debarring poor modeſt Chriſtians</hi> from what in Gods ſight they have, it may be more right to than many others, who can <hi>talk</hi> better and more; as well, as there ought to be a <hi>juſt caution</hi> in the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Perſons,</hi> who may be <hi>vitious and ſcandalous.</hi> However, for my own part I muſt ſay, that I would in this caſe be under a great Dread and Fear, to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> any poor Soul, in whom I think I ſee, (tho' in a ſmall degree, and <hi>as a grain of muſtard ſeed,) Aliquid Chriſti,</hi> any thing of Chriſts Image: For I judge we err more ſafely on the ſide of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> (if indeed it be poſſible ſo to err)
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41864:60"/> than on the ſide of <hi>a precipitant and preſumptuous judging</hi> of ones <hi>ſtate and fitneſs,</hi> from <hi>Rules</hi> of our own preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing; when none can tell me, <hi>what the leaſt degree of ſincerity and grace is which God doth accept, and which gives one right to participate of all Ordinances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She was a <hi>careful and impartial Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Scriptures,</hi> which ſhe read with great judgment and obſervation, with the uſe of the beſt helps, ſhe could have for that end. But though ſhe ſtudied to underſtand <hi>every part</hi> of <hi>Scripture;</hi> yet ſhe was moſt converſant in the <hi>more ſpiritual</hi> parts thereof. She took many a <hi>mental walk</hi> in the <hi>delicious Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of</hi> Davids <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and ſat oft with <hi>great pleaſure,</hi> under <hi>the cloſe Arbour of</hi> Solomon's <hi>ſong;</hi> which, as ſhe learned over by heart (as to the Words) in her Childhood; ſo attained, in a great meaſure, both to underſtand and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in her riper years.</p>
               <p>And, together with the Scriptures, ſhe read, with great pains and judgment, many of the <hi>moſt ſolid and practical En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Writers;</hi> as <hi>her Books</hi> ſhe hath left behind will witneſs to ſuch as have them, when they ſee the many <hi>Marginal Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> wherewith ſhe hath filled them,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41864:61"/> according as ſhe was edified and affected her ſelf with what ſhe read. And tho' her Characters be ſuch, as none can well underſtand; yet the conſideration of <hi>thoſe Truths,</hi> that ſhe thereby points at, will diſcover both the <hi>judiciouſneſs</hi> and <hi>ſeriouſneſs</hi> of her ſpirit. And I hope theſe very hints, (though it may be not diſtinctly apprehended) may be a <hi>leading Example of ſeriouſneſs and piety to her ſurviving Relatives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She was <hi>laborious</hi> and almoſt unweari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Duty,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Faſting and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> which laſt <hi>Ordinance</hi> ſeemed to be the very <hi>food</hi> ſhe lived on, and the <hi>air</hi> ſhe breathed in. <hi>She hungred and thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after God, as the hart after the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter books;</hi> and would often pleaſantly reflect on an expreſſion of Mr. <hi>Ruther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foords</hi> to that purpoſe (in his Book of <hi>Letters</hi> which ſhe greatly delighted in) and ſay, I think <hi>God feeds me with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, viz.</hi> After the enjoyment of God, and manifeſtations of his Love.</p>
               <p>She was <hi>zealouſly bent</hi> to advance Gods Honour, and propagate the Goſpel, (which I hope <hi>others</hi> will imitate her in,) and uſed to ſay, <hi>For what elſe hath God given me life, and any ſhare of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things.</hi> And, upon this account, her
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41864:61"/> Temper being naturally timerous, ſhe would oft with great earneſtneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of her ſelf, <hi>That ſhe feared her fears were ſuch, as might diſhonour God, and diſparage her Profeſſion in the eyes of ſuch as are without;</hi> though yet her fears were more viſible to her ſelf than any elſe.</p>
               <p>However, this fearful Temper did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent <hi>Death</hi> to her oft in <hi>Melancholly Ideas:</hi> Yet ſhe would commonly ſay, <hi>I fear not to be dead, but only to dye; neither do I fear Death ſo properly, as the very fears thereof.</hi> Upon which account, ſhe would oft chide her ſelf, as acting ſo irrationally and unchriſtianly. But God gave her, in a great meaſure, the Conqueſt over ſuch Fears before her Death. However, this Temper of hers made her oft ſay, That for her own part, ſhe could never joyn with that <hi>Prayer,</hi> (in the <hi>Service-Book) From ſudden Death deliver us:</hi> For ſhe feared a <hi>lingring</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a <hi>ſudden death;</hi> which God in ſome meaſure did ſatisfie her in.</p>
               <p>In the midſt of her <hi>Complainings</hi> on whatever account, ſhe would ſtill break out with a <hi>Caution</hi> to her ſelf; <hi>But what do I? I muſt praiſe as well as pray; for my mercies are more than my wants:</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:41864:62"/> 
                  <hi>yea, even my wants may be my mercy.</hi> And therefore ſhe would beg the aſſiſtance of others in this work; and ſay, <hi>I deſire you to praiſe as well as pray on my account.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea (which may ſeem ſtrange) not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding her fears as to her ſelf, ſhe was of a bold and confident Temper in the <hi>publick Concerns of Religion;</hi> and would not eaſily be ſhaken in her reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions that way, whatever Oppoſition or Reflection ſhe might meet with on that account from an ignorant World: And, if there were <hi>any</hi> that thought or ſpoke contemptuouſly of <hi>ſerious piety,</hi> ſhe could not but with <hi>generous pity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion</hi> reflect upon them.</p>
               <p>She had a very particular regard for <hi>her Relatives and Friends,</hi> eſpecially as to what might be conducive to the real profit of their Souls. And I may ſay, <hi>That ſhe travelled as it were in birth for her Children a ſecond time, that ſhe might ſee Chriſt formed in them.</hi> And, I hope, that as God was pleaſed to give her much ſatisfaction in this before her death; ſo her Prayers may come to be yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwered, in due time, this way.</p>
               <p>She had attained a <hi>well-grounded Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of her <hi>Intereſt in God and Chriſt:</hi> which, (to my obſervation) ſhe never
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41864:62"/> actually doubted of, even in the midſt of Temptations. Although, her natural Temper being ſuſpitious, and not eaſily ſatisfied in ſuch a grand concern, ſhe would oft put up <hi>Queſtions,</hi> as to this matter, (to ſuch as ſhe could be free with) in ſuch a way, as if ſhe ſeemed to doubt thereof; and would oft ſay, <hi>If it be ſo and ſo with me, why am I thus?</hi> Yet (as ſhe hath intimated to ſome) this was rather, that ſhe might be further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied from the <hi>Reaſons of others,</hi> as well as from her <hi>own Evidences;</hi> for ſhe thought ſhe could never be <hi>too ſure</hi> of this weighty and concerning <hi>Buſineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She had ſeveral times ſome <hi>unuſual Impreſsions</hi> of things upon her Spirit, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in <hi>Dreams;</hi> which, though ſhe was cautious not to lay too great a ſtreſs on; <hi>(for ſhe founded on a ſurer word of Testimony;</hi> yet ſhe could not but take particular notice of. At one time, ſaid ſhe, (for I give this in her own words as near as I can remember) <q>I dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that I ſaw <hi>the repreſentation of two Humane Bodies,</hi> but ſo glorious above what our frail Bodies are here, as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of no compariſon. They were, to my Apprehenſion, like <hi>the fineſt and pureſt Amber, with Rays proceeding from</hi>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:41864:63"/> 
                     <hi>them like the ſhinings and glances of Diamonds or Rubies;</hi> and <hi>ſo tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> that the <hi>beautiful contexture</hi> and <hi>motion</hi> of the <hi>internal parts</hi> appeared no leſs plainly to me, than the <hi>exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal figure.</hi> Which, whilſt with Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhment I looked upon, methoughts it was ſuggeſted to me, <hi>Such ſhall the Bodies of the Saints at the Reſurrection be.</hi> This extraordinary Dream ſhe would</q> ſpeak of ſometimes in theſe or the like words; but never without a ſenſible <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion and emphaſis,</hi> which added to the pleaſure of hearing the <hi>Account.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At another time, (in the midſt of one of her tedious <hi>Exerciſes)</hi> falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, ſhe ſeemed (according to her own expreſſion) to be <hi>ſtruggling and confli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting with two Hands;</hi> which, as ſhe thought, did at laſt ſo <hi>tyre</hi> her out, that ſhe was ready to <hi>ſuccumb,</hi> her ſtrength quite failing her: In the midſt of which plunge and difficulty, <hi>another Hand</hi> quite different from the former, and of a more pleaſant and lovely aſpect, came in to her <hi>aſſiſtance;</hi> and not only <hi>ſtruggled</hi> with the former Hands, until it <hi>overcame</hi> them; but, in the mean time, did ſweetly <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and refreſh</hi> her. And, ſaid ſhe, I thought that the reflection I had of this
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41864:63"/> matter at that time, was, That <hi>the two. Hands</hi> I was conflicting with, <hi>were Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Temptation;</hi> and that <hi>the Hand</hi> that came to my relief, <hi>was the Hand of the Almighty,</hi> put forth in the <hi>Aids</hi> of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> thorow <hi>Christ,</hi> to carry me ſafely thorow all my <hi>Tryals.</hi> Which, when ſhe was relating, one ſaid, May not the two Hands be ſuppoſed as well to mean <hi>Temptation and Affliction?</hi> To which ſhe humbly replyed: <hi>I include Affliction under the notion of Temptation; but what ever be left out, Corruption muſt be reckoned to be included.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Subject,</hi> for the moſt part, of all her <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> with <hi>ſerious Perſons,</hi> was ſtill <hi>divine and ſpiritual.</hi> And if at any time the <hi>ſtrain</hi> of the Diſcourſe were turned otherwiſe, ſhe would be ready to ſay, <hi>Come, let us leave ſuch petty Matters, and talk of what deſerves our Thoughts and Conſiderations.</hi> And when ſhe could not come at <hi>her Friends,</hi> with whom ſhe <hi>could be moſt free;</hi> ſhe would be ſure to afford them ſome <hi>Work</hi> by <hi>Letters</hi> on <hi>ſuch Subjects,</hi> as might be mutually edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying. And indeed, in Writing, ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly expreſs'd her ſelf in a ſingular <hi>vein,</hi> both as to <hi>Spirituality</hi> and <hi>Good Thought.</hi> And as to this, I hope it may
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41864:64"/> not be unedifying to name you two or three Paſſages amongſt many.</p>
               <p>Writing to a Friend, concerning her ſpiritual ſtate, ſhe thus expreſſes her ſelf.—<q>I muſt acknowledge that I am uſeing the <hi>Means of Grace,</hi> as much as I am able, with that little meaſure of <hi>Faith</hi> I have, (in a ſenſe of great <hi>Guilt</hi> daily contracted,) ſo as to have conſtant recourſe <hi>to the blood of ſprinkling,</hi> for <hi>Cleanſing and Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> whence I have attained <hi>peace</hi> as to the <hi>matter of Jeſtification.</hi> And I muſt alſo acknowledge that I <hi>am waiting and depending on Chriſt dayly for the Influences of his Spirit every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for the <hi>aſſiſting</hi> me to <hi>reſiſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, mortifie corruptions, and perform hard and difficult duties</hi> (as indeed <hi>all duties</hi> are to me,) <hi>as alſo to bear up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der afflictions.</hi> But I muſt tell you, that here lies the very <hi>streſs</hi> of my <hi>Tryal,</hi> that God ſeems not (at leaſt ſenſibly to me) to make out his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as to the <hi>proportioning his ſupplies of ſtrength,</hi> according <hi>as my day of trouble and tryal is.</hi> I might here take up all the <hi>expreſſions</hi> of <hi>lamentation</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>bewail</hi> my ſtate. But I <hi>check</hi> my ſelf and acquieſce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41864:64"/> it is the Lord that does it. And ſure I am, it is not ſo much <hi>comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manifeſtations,</hi> that I deſire, as <hi>ſupporting grace,</hi> that I may carry to the honour of Religion. But my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is ſuſpicious, and I am always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting <hi>new troubles;</hi> for <hi>waves call on waves</hi> in my caſe. You tell me, <hi>that we are in ſtorms to hope for calms. as well as in calms to prepare for ſtorms.</hi> And I grant it ſhould be ſo. But I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe notwithſtanding, that you are not ignorant; <hi>that it is more eaſy for us, when in the light, to diſcern a cloud at a diſtance; than it is to ſee any thing in the dark diſtinctly, a far off eſpecially.</hi> But I will <hi>conclude,</hi> with what has been much on my mind, I mean <hi>Herbert's Poem,</hi> called, <hi>Bitter-Sweet;</hi> which I <hi>return</hi> you, with ſome Variation and Alteration, and which I think does now exactly hold forth my Caſe.</q>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My</hi> Dear, <hi>tho'</hi> Abſent Lord,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Since thou canſt</hi> Love, <hi>yet</hi> Hide,</l>
                  <l>Withdraw, <hi>and yet</hi> ſupport;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I will thy</hi> Will abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I will</hi> Complain <hi>and</hi> Pray,</l>
                  <l>Bewail <hi>and yet</hi> Approve;</l>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:41864:65"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And all my</hi> Gloomy Days,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I will</hi> Believe <hi>and</hi> Love.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>At another ſhe thus Writes.—<q>I am fully <hi>ſatisfied</hi> there may be much <hi>Love</hi> in <hi>Corrections: For what Child is there that the Father Chaſtneth not?</hi> And my earneſt deſire is, That while my <hi>Father</hi> keeps the <hi>Rod</hi> in his hand, I may hang about him, and never ceaſe <hi>my wrestling Supplications,</hi> until I get the ſanctified uſe of <hi>Afflictions.</hi> But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, this is not the ſad part of my <hi>Caſe,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> does not carry it to me, as a <hi>most wiſe, merciful, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Father in all things:</hi> But it lyes here, <hi>That I do not carry it as the Child of ſuch a Father, with that filial, believing, reſigning, cheerful frame and temper of Spirit,</hi> that is <hi>ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him,</hi> and <hi>ſo ſutable</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> But I adore <hi>the Wiſdom of his Love,</hi> even in his <hi>Withdrawings.</hi> But Oh! how can I be ſatisfied with my ſelf, in not imitating more fully the <hi>Saints of old,</hi> (and ſome I know <hi>yet alive)</hi> who breathed after the <hi>better Country:</hi> Which <hi>Temper</hi> God hath ſo far <hi>owned</hi> and <hi>honoured,</hi> as to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn, <hi>That therefore he is not aſhamed</hi>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:41864:65"/> 
                     <hi>to be called their God.</hi> This, this, would be an effectual <hi>Remedy</hi> againſt all my <hi>Diſtempers:</hi> Which therefore I pray for it, and deſire you to do ſo alſo on my account.</q>
               </p>
               <p>She earneſtly and conſtantly <hi>prayed for and. breathed after the Influences of the Spirit.</hi> Her thoughts of which ſhe thus expreſſes to a Friend.—<q>Since God hath ſo freely promiſed <hi>to give his Spirit to thoſe that ask it;</hi> have we not great <hi>Incouragement</hi> thence, to deſire and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg for a more <hi>plentiful effuſion</hi> thereof upon us; that it may be, <hi>as water upon the thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground; that our wilderneſs may bloſſom as the Roſe, and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert barren hearts be turned into a fruitful Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, irriguated with Springs of Living water.</hi> For by theſe and many ſuch <hi>figurative Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> in Scripture I underſtand <hi>the powering forth of the Spirit</hi> upon us: And the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them hath been very <hi>ſupporting</hi> to me under my preſent wants and unfruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a great <hi>incouragement</hi> to wait and hope in God, that it ſhall be better in due time. Oh this <hi>bleſſed Spirit!</hi> What a change would it make in the <hi>world,</hi> and on <hi>particular perſons,</hi> were it given more plentifully. For which let us pray, that it may be given as an <hi>Inlightning Spirit,</hi> as a <hi>Guiding and Conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit,</hi> as a <hi>Quickning and Comforting Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> This would make us walk more <hi>holyly</hi>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:41864:66"/> 
                     <hi>and humbly,</hi> more <hi>prudently and wiſely,</hi> more <hi>thankfully and chearfully,</hi> more <hi>above our fears and ſorrows,</hi> with more <hi>Chriſtian courage and fortitude of Spirit,</hi> throughout our whole <hi>courſe,</hi> and with a <hi>temper</hi> more becoming <hi>the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſuch a Father,</hi> and <hi>the Heirs of ſuch an inheritance.</hi> Would not this make <hi>you</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the high and noble work of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi> and make you more uſefull and ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in <hi>Preaching</hi> the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel?</hi> And would not this make <hi>us both</hi> more ſervicable in our <hi>ſeveral ſtations</hi> and capacities, to <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God,</hi> which is the <hi>great end</hi> of our <hi>Lives,</hi> and I hope the <hi>great deſire</hi> of our <hi>Souls.</hi> And therefore I know nothing more worthy of our moſt earneſt wreſtlings and greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities. For, ſince I hope God hath given us <hi>an intereſt</hi> in himſelf, thorow his dear Son and our great Mediator; <hi>and ſo hath accepted our Perſous in Juſtification, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the imputed righteouſneſs of Chriſt:</hi> I think the next work we have to do, is <hi>to be day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interceding for the Influences of the Spirit in order to carry on the great buſineſs of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> that ſo we may grow in a <hi>fitneſs</hi> for every <hi>duty,</hi> and a <hi>meetneſs</hi> for the <hi>future ſtate,</hi> that we are haſtning into.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It were long to produce all or many of the Expreſſions of this nature that might be given. And therefore I ſhall only add one more, in a
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:41864:66"/> 
                  <hi>Letter</hi> to <hi>a Friend;</hi> upon a <hi>Reprieve from Death,</hi> that ſhe had providentially got beyond expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for a time, and which ſhe was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive <hi>he</hi> had ſome hand in, (with <q>others,) as a Return of Prayer.—Now <hi>methinks</hi> (ſays ſhe) I have been ſaying to you, <hi>(whom</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to have been <hi>inſtrumental</hi> in this <hi>matter,)</hi> is this <hi>your kindneſs</hi> to <hi>your Friend?</hi> When I ſeem'd to have got ſo near to the <hi>harbour</hi> of an hoped for <hi>reſt,</hi> to uſe all your <hi>force and ſtrength,</hi> to bring me back again into this <hi>ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and troubleſome Sea,</hi> where I muſt expect to be <hi>toſſed</hi> with new <hi>Tempeſts,</hi> before I get to <hi>ſhore;</hi> of <hi>which I have now a much clearer Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, than of any ſervice I can do here in this world.</hi> Did I ever deſire you to <hi>pray for Life?</hi> Or was it not rather, that I might be carried thorow <hi>the dark valley of the ſhadow of Death?</hi> But I muſt ſubmit, ſince I know you think you have <hi>acted Duty</hi> in this; and ſince all things of this nature are <hi>ordered</hi> by a wiſe and gracious God for good to us. And this does abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfie me in <hi>this,</hi> and I hope in all other <hi>diſpenſations</hi> concerning me.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And now from theſe <hi>few Expreſſions,</hi> as well as from <hi>what hints</hi> have been beſides given of this <hi>pious Perſon,</hi> we may eaſily perceive <hi>what Spirit ſhe was of, and what her great work and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the world was.</hi> She wiſely choſe the <hi>Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part,</hi> which none could take from her: The
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41864:67"/> whole of her <hi>Life</hi> being one <hi>continued declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſhe ſought a better Country;</hi> as knowing <hi>that we have no continuing City or place of abode here. Thorow a patient continuance in well-doing, ſhe ſought for honour and glory and immortality, both in Health and Sickneſs.</hi> And, tho' an <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Decay of Spirits,</hi> (in Gods <hi>wiſe determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,)</hi> did incapacitate her, in the <hi>hour of Deaths approach,</hi> from having <hi>that ſenſible joy and raviſhment,</hi> which <hi>ſomtimes</hi> the Saints then have, <hi>from the proſpect of the nearneſs of Glory;</hi> yet <hi>that Faith and Affiance, that Reverence and Love, and that Reſignation and full ſatisfaction,</hi> which ſhe then expreſſed, were ſuch <hi>clear Evidences</hi> of her <hi>Grace,</hi> and ſuch <hi>happy Prognoſticks</hi> of that <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs</hi> ſhe was entering upon the <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of; that we may juſtly admire Gods Mercy in all this, both to Her and Us.</p>
               <p>And now, <hi>my Friends,</hi> obey the <hi>Instruction</hi> and imitate the <hi>Pattern</hi> that I have at this time ſet before you. Which that we may do, let us fervently implore the <hi>divine Grace,</hi> and ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improve the <hi>Goſpel-Means.</hi> And then I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not, but we ſhall come in due time to find this <hi>Doctrine</hi> verified in our own <hi>Experience; That better is the Day of Death, than the Day of Birth.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:41864:67"/>
            <head>TO THE MEMORY of the Truly Religious, Mrs. <hi>Suſanna Soame;</hi> WHO Departed this Life at <hi>Thurlow</hi> in <hi>Suffolk, Feb. 14. An. Dom.</hi> 169 1/2.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ART thou then gone, thou ſweet and humble <hi>Mind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leaving thy <hi>Friends</hi> thus ſorrowing behind?</l>
               <l>And can our <hi>Thoughts</hi> within our <hi>breaſts</hi> be pent,</l>
               <l>Since ſorrows double are, that have no vent?</l>
               <l>No! No! <hi>My weeping Muſe</hi> ſhall drop a Verſe,</l>
               <l>And offer at thy much lamented <hi>Hearſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Piety and Worth</hi> deſerve no leſs:</l>
               <l>And if my <hi>Lines</hi> be in an humble <hi>Dreſs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It yet may <hi>Mourners</hi> ſuit, ſince 'tis requir'd,</l>
               <l>That ſuch in <hi>Black,</hi> not <hi>Gold,</hi> ſhould be attir'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had I a Pen drop't from an <hi>Angels Wing,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or could I hear the <hi>Anthems</hi> thou doſt ſing;</l>
               <l>Since thou art joyn'd unto the <hi>Quire</hi> above,</l>
               <l>And ſwallow'd up in <hi>Raptures</hi> high of Love:</l>
               <l>My <hi>Thoughts</hi> might then, 'tis like, my <hi>Pen</hi> inſpire,</l>
               <l>with ſuch like <hi>Notes,</hi> as mov'd Wiſe <hi>Sol'mons Lyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When he did ſing the <hi>Myſtick Loves</hi> between</l>
               <l>Heav'ns <hi>Glorious Darling</hi> and his <hi>Purchas'd Queen:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For now that <hi>Song</hi> (thou lov'dſt ſo here) is known</l>
               <l>To thee, ſince thou haſt reach'd the <hi>Heavenly Throne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet when I think, how <hi>Holy Paul</hi> before,</l>
               <l>Tho' thus rapt up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> could do no more,</l>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:41864:68"/>
               <l>But only tell he ſaw <hi>Things Glorious,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which he nor could nor durſt expreſs to us:</l>
               <l>I'me therefore left in <hi>ſilence</hi> to adore,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Hand</hi> which caſts a <hi>Veil</hi> ſuch things before,</l>
               <l>And wills us to believe they are too great</l>
               <l>For this <hi>Imperfect State,</hi> where we await,</l>
               <l>Until we alſo from our <hi>Corps</hi> remove,</l>
               <l>And mount all Earthly Duſt and Shades, above.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wherefore I'm left to muſe <hi>on what is past,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And on thy <hi>by-gone-Liſe</hi> ſome Thoughts to caſt;</l>
               <l>And here, methinks, as preſent ſtill to day,</l>
               <l>I ſee thy <hi>Face,</hi> and hear <hi>thee thus to ſay;</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <head>
               <hi>[An</hi> Acroſtical Character <hi>of her</hi> Life.]</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi> oar fain I would above each earthly thing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi> nto my Lord, of all my Joy, the Spring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi> uch is my <hi>ſtudy,</hi> but alas! I find</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> ll my <hi>Attempts</hi> too weak, too dark my <hi>Mind;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi> ow <hi>Clouds</hi> bemiſt me, <hi>Grief</hi> o're-pow'rs my Soul,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi> ow <hi>Fears</hi> alternate like the Waves do rowl,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> nd all my Comforts, Joy and Hope controul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi> weet <hi>Glances</hi> from my God, yet now and then,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> blidge my Soul from Sorrow to refrain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> nd blaſt my <hi>Griefs,</hi> and cauſe my <hi>Fears</hi> to fly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M</hi> y Caſe thus changeth too and fro, whilſt I</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi> ach day <hi>for Heaven long,</hi> yet <hi>fear to dye.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet, tho' all is but Folly that is ſaid</l>
               <l>By <hi>Living Mortals</hi> of th' <hi>Immortal Dead:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet ſince we juſtly do conclude thou'rt bleſt,</l>
               <l>And now from Pains and Sorrows all at reſt,</l>
               <l>Methinks I hear <hi>thy Voice</hi> from Heaven high,</l>
               <l>Drop ſilent to my <hi>Ear</hi> thus through the <hi>Sky;</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:41864:68"/>
            <head>
               <hi>[An</hi> Acroſtical Character <hi>of her</hi> Death.]</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>oar now I do, above each earthly thing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  </hi>nto my Lord of all my Joy the Spring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>uch was my <hi>Aim below,</hi> but then did find</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>ll my <hi>Attempts</hi> too weak, too dark my <hi>Mind:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>o <hi>Cloud</hi> bemiſts me now, and on my Soul,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>o <hi>Grief</hi> or <hi>Fear</hi> alternately doth rowl,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>s an <hi>Allay</hi> my Comforts to controul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>weet <hi>Sights</hi> of God and Chriſt I do obtain:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> ſweet my <hi>Life!</hi> Sweet <hi>Place</hi> where I remain!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> are now my Company;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M</hi>y <hi>Friends</hi> below I'd pity, did not I,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>xpect to ſee them to <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>The Epitaph.</head>
            <l>UNderneath this <hi>Stone</hi> doth lye</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Duſt</hi> precious, for the <hi>Memory</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of a <hi>ſweet Saint,</hi> who once did dwell</l>
            <l>In ſuch a <hi>fadeing Mortal Cell:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who having got <hi>Gods Paſs,</hi> took <hi>wing</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Upwards to <hi>Heaven,</hi> to live and ſing</l>
            <l>Triumphant Hallelujahs <hi>there,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>breath more free</hi> in <hi>Sweeter Air.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <head>An Acroſtical Memorial.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>S</hi>ince <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               </hi>pwards <hi>S</hi>oar'd, <hi>A</hi>ll <hi>N</hi>otions <hi>N</hi>ew <hi>A</hi>ttend <hi>S</hi>een <hi>O</hi>bjects: <hi>A</hi>ncient <hi>M</hi>oleſtations <hi>E</hi>nd.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>As the laſt <hi>Expreſſion</hi> of <hi>Friendſhip</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> Theſe <hi>Lines</hi> are Offered by R. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41864:69"/>
            <head>BOOKS <hi>Printed for</hi> John Harris, <hi>at the</hi> Harrow <hi>againſt the Church in the</hi> Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, <hi>and</hi> John Salusbury <hi>at the</hi> Riſing Sun <hi>over againſt the</hi> Royal Exchange <hi>in</hi> Cornhil.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>ANgliae Metropolis:</hi> Or, The Preſent State of <hi>London,</hi> with Memorials comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a full and ſuccienct Account of the Antient and Modern State thereof. Firſt Written by the late Ingenious <hi>Tho. De Laune</hi> Gent. and continued to this preſent Year, by a careful Hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Life and Death of that Old Diſciple of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and Eminent Miniſter of the Goſpel, Mr. <hi>Hanſerd Knollys,</hi> who dyed in the Ninety Third Year of his Age. Theſe Two Printed for <hi>J. Harris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Certainly of the <hi>Worlds of Spirits.</hi> Fully evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by unqueſtionable Hiſtories of Apparitions and Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts, Operations, Voices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Proving the Immortality of Souls, the Malice and Miſeries of the Devils and the Damned, and the Bleſſedneſs of the Juſtified. By <hi>R. Baxter</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. An End of Doctrinal Controverſies which have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Troubled the Churches by Reconciling Explication, without much Diſputing. By <hi>R. Baxter.</hi> Theſe Two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for <hi>J. Salusbury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>CORRIGENDA.</head>
            <p>SErm. 1. pag. 7. lin. 20: after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> inſert <hi>and.</hi> p. 17. l. 20. after <hi>follow</hi> inſert <hi>that.</hi> p. 28. l. 10. after <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> inſert <hi>expreſſed.</hi> p. 45. l. 1. for <hi>ſhe</hi> read <hi>they.</hi> p. 47. l. 14. after <hi>which</hi> inſert <hi>is.</hi> p. 48. l. 8. after <hi>her</hi> inſert <hi>to obſerve her.</hi> Serm. 2. p. 55. l. ult. after <hi>muſt</hi> inſert <hi>not.</hi> p. 72. l. 7. for <hi>Eph.</hi> read <hi>Ep.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41864:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
